<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of the revolution in Portugal in the year, 1640, or, An account of their revolt from Spain and setting the crown on the head of Don John of Braganza, father to Don Pedro, the present king and Catharine, Queen Dowager of England / written in French by the excellent pen of the Abbot Vertot ... ; and done into English.</title>
            <title>Histoire de la conjuration de Portugal en 1640. English</title>
            <author>Vertot, abbé de, 1655-1735.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 93 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A71204</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V272</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2177</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43002</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07896653</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07896653</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40321</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A71204)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40321)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1217:8 or 1720:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of the revolution in Portugal in the year, 1640, or, An account of their revolt from Spain and setting the crown on the head of Don John of Braganza, father to Don Pedro, the present king and Catharine, Queen Dowager of England / written in French by the excellent pen of the Abbot Vertot ... ; and done into English.</title>
                  <title>Histoire de la conjuration de Portugal en 1640. English</title>
                  <author>Vertot, abbé de, 1655-1735.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 176 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Mat. Gilliflower ...[and 4 others],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 176.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 176.</note>
                  <note>This item appears at reel 1217:8 as Wing V272, and at reel 1720:8 as Wing H2177 (number in Wing 2nd ed., but not in Wing CD-ROM, 1996).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in the British Library and the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Portugal --  History --  Revolution, 1640 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Portugal --  History --  Modern, 1580-</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40321:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40321:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY OF THE Revolution in <hi>Portugal,</hi> In the Year, 1640.</p>
            <p>Or, An Account of their Revolt from <hi>Spain,</hi> And ſetting the Crown on the Head of <hi>Don John</hi> of <hi>Braganza,</hi> Father to <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> the Preſent King, and <hi>Catharine</hi> Queen Dowager of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written in <hi>French</hi> by the excellent Pen of the Abbot <hi>Vertat,</hi> (Author of the Hiſtory of the Revolution in <hi>Sweden.</hi>) And done into <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Mat. Gilliflower, Tim. Goodwin, Mat. Wotton, Rich. Parker,</hi> and <hi>Benj. Tooke.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:40321:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40321:2"/>
            <head>The Introduction.</head>
            <p>AMong the Principal Events of this laſt Age, none de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves our Attention more than the Revolt of <hi>Portugal,</hi> in the Year One Thouſand Six Hundred and Forty. The Unanimity, Zeal, and Secrecy with which this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy was carried on for a long time, between Perſons of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Ages, Sexes, and Qualities; the Ardour for recovering their Liberties, which animated them to encounter Difficulties, in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance inſuperable; and laſtly,
<pb facs="tcp:40321:3"/> the compleat Succeſs, and the little Blood loſt in the execution of this mighty Enterprize, makes it truly admirable and ſurpriſing.</p>
            <p>This ſmall Fragment, as it were torn from the general Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Times, was written in <hi>French</hi> not very long ſince as an Eſſay by the Abbot <hi>Vertat,</hi> ſince Author of the <hi>Hiſtory of the Revolutions of</hi> Sweden; both which Pieces have been received with the Applauſe of the Publick. The Materials out of which he has compiled this ſmall Volume, are for the moſt part<note n="*" place="bottom">Portugal reſtaurado de Menezes Caet. Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarel. Luſitania reparata de Macedo, Mercure Francois de Renandot Siry, et Recueil de Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions extraordinaires.</note> Printed Accounts, Journals, Gazettes, and
<pb facs="tcp:40321:3"/> the Relations of Perſons who were at <hi>Lisbon</hi> when this <hi>Drama</hi> was acted. Moſt of theſe are indeed ill enough writ, but have receiv'd a new Life and Luſtre ſince they have been touch'd by his Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Pen. I might, in this place, commend the Vivacity, Politeneſs, and Fidelity with which this little Piece is writ; but I ſhall rather chuſe to give the Reader a view of the State of Affairs which lead to that Revolution, which is the Subject of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Portugal</hi> was firſt erected in the Year 1139. into a Kingdom by <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſo</hi> I. who, after he had defeated the <hi>Moors,</hi> refuſed to pay that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to <hi>Spain</hi> which his Father had done. After him <hi>Alphonſo</hi> III his Great Grandſon, had <hi>Algarva</hi> given him
<pb facs="tcp:40321:4"/> in Dowry with the Princeſs <hi>Beatrix,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Alphonſo</hi> the Tenth King of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> which ſtill gives a Title to the Heir Apparent of the Crown. Thus <hi>Portugal</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued an Independant Kingdom, Governed by its own Princes, till the Brave <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> unfortunately periſhed in the Battel of <hi>Alcazar, Aug.</hi> 4. 1578. without leaving any Iſſue behind him. The Cardinal <hi>Dom Henry,</hi> his Great Uncle, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to the Throne, whoſe Reign laſted but ſixteen Months. After his Death, divers Princes and Princeſſes pretended to the Crown. <hi>Catharine,</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Braganza, Philip</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Spain,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and <hi>Dom Antonio,</hi> Grand Prior of <hi>Crete,</hi> were all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended
<pb facs="tcp:40321:4"/> from <hi>Dom Emanuel,</hi> Father of the Cardinal King, but in different Degrees: There was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Dutcheſs of <hi>Braganza,</hi> and the K. of <hi>Spain</hi> in the ſame Degree and neareſt the Crown. <hi>Catharine</hi> was Daughter to the Infant <hi>Edward,</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> was Son to the Empreſs <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> both Children to <hi>Dom Emanuel.</hi> The Grand Prior was only Natural Son to the Infant <hi>Dom Lewis,</hi> Second Son of <hi>Dom Emanuel,</hi> but his Party gave out, there was a ſecret Marriage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween that Prince and his Mother. <hi>Catharine de Medicis,</hi> Queen of <hi>France</hi> ſent a Deputation to the States, to repreſent her Title as deſcended from <hi>Alphonſo</hi> III. King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and <hi>Maud</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Bolonia.</hi> The Pope too put in, and drew
<pb facs="tcp:40321:5"/> an Advantage from King <hi>Henry</hi>'s dying a Cardinal; but all theſe Pretenſions were little conſidered. All were agreed, and the moſt able Lawyers had determined, that the apparent Right was in the Dutcheſs of <hi>Braganza,</hi> not only becauſe the Laws of the Kingdom exclude Foreigners from ſucceeding to the Crown; but likewiſe by the Right of Lineal Deſcent, as Daughter of the Infant <hi>Edward,</hi> whoſe Title could not be diſputed by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his Siſter, Mother to the King of <hi>Spain.</hi> And doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, this Dutcheſs would have been acknowledged as Queen of <hi>Portugal,</hi> had ſhe had the Power neceſſary to aſſert her Rightful Pretenſions.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40321:5"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY OF THE <hi>Revolution</hi> IN <hi>PORTUGAL,</hi> In the Year 1640.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Spaniards</hi> had been near<note n="*" place="bottom">Since the Year 1581.</note> Threeſcore Years in Poſſeſſion of the Crown of <hi>Portugal. Philip</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Spain,</hi> after the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40321:6"/> Death of <hi>Henry</hi> Cardinal-King, had forced it from the Houſe of <hi>Braganza,</hi> by the help of a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable Army, the beſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſupport a bad Title. This Kingdom was by degrees become a Province of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the <hi>Portugueſe</hi> ſeem'd for ever to deſpair of ſhaking off their Chains. The Great Men did not dare to appear in a Splendor ſuitable to their Rank, or demand a due Reſpect, for fear of raiſing Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Miniſters, at a time when the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a man's Wealth, Family, or Merit, were enough to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him ſuſpected, and expoſe him to ill Uſage. The Gentry were baniſh'd to their Country Seats, and the People oppreſs'd with Exceſſive Taxes.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:40321:6"/>
            <p>It was a Maxim with the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de</hi> Duke <hi>d' Olivarez,</hi> Firſt Miniſter to <hi>Philip</hi> the Fourth King of <hi>Spain,</hi> That <hi>New Conqueſts ought to be exhauſted.</hi> He knew very well the Ancient and Natural Antipathy of theſe Neighbouring Nations muſt needs render the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Government hateful to the <hi>Portugueſe;</hi> and that Nation could never tamely ſee all Places in the State fill'd with Strangers, or Fellows of mean Extraction, whoſe only Merit was their entire Devotion to the Court. For this Reaſon he thought the beſt way to eſtabliſh his Maſter's Power, was, To exclude the Nobility and Gentry from all Employs and Publick Truſt, and by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly impoveriſhing the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40321:7"/> to leave them incapable of attempting any Alteration in the State. Beſides this, He judged it neceſſary to drain the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Flower of their Youth, and the beſt who could bear Arms, and to employ them in Foreign Wars, to prevent ſuch Dangerous People from diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Repoſe of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>This Conduct, which poſſibly might have ſucceeded, if it had been carried to a certain pitch; being ſtrained too high, had a quite contrary effect, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded partly from the Diſtreſs in which the Court was at that time, and partly from the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per then of the Firſt Miniſter, naturally ſtiff and inflexible.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40321:7"/> They began now to diſregard all Meaſures with <hi>Portugal,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining to uſe the ordinary Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences for raiſing Money on a People. In ſhort, they ſeem'd more to exact a Contribution in an Enemy's Country, than a juſt Impoſition on Subjects. The <hi>Portugueſe</hi> having nothing more to loſe, and deſpairing to ſee an end or mitigation of their Miſery, as long as they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in their preſent condition, began now to think of freeing themſelves from the Severity of their cruel Maſters, which they had ever eſteem'd Uſurpers, and intolerable Tyrants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Margaret,</hi> Ducheſs of <hi>Mantua,</hi> govern'd <hi>Portugal</hi> at that time in Quality of Vice-Queen; but
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40321:8"/> this was but a glittering Title which the Court has given to a very limited Power. The ſecret Counſels, and the great Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Affairs, were entruſted in the Hands of <hi>Moguel Vaſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellos,</hi> a <hi>Portugueſe,</hi> who had the Character of Secretary of State to the Vice-Queen, but was indeed an Abſolute and Independent Miniſter.</p>
            <p>This Man receiv'd his Orders immediately from the <hi>Conde</hi> Duke, whoſe Creature he was, with whom he had ingratiated, and made himſelf neceſſary by a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Art he had of drawing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually conſiderable Sums out of <hi>Portugal;</hi> and an intrieguing Wit, which enabl'd him to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh his private Deſigns. He had
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40321:8"/> the Art of raiſing Feuds and Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities among the Great Men of the Kingdom, which He would craftily foment by his Favour, and affected Diſtinctions, by which he was ſure to pleaſe and engage thoſe who received them, and to create Spite and Envy in the reſt. While theſe Diviſions continued, he concluded all was ſafe, perſuading himſelf the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending Parties would be wholly employ'd in ſatisfying their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments, and not have leiſure to attempt any thing againſt the ſetled Government.</p>
            <p>There was no Man in <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal</hi> beſides the Duke of <hi>Bragan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za,</hi> who could give the <hi>Spaniards</hi> the leaſt Diſquiet. This Prince was of a mild and ſweet Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40321:9"/> a Lover of Eaſe; more a Man of Good Senſe, than Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Wit. In Buſineſs he went to the main Point; and eaſily made himſelf Maſter of what he apply'd himſelf to, but ſeldom cared for Application. Duke <hi>Theodoſius</hi> his Father, a Hot and Violent Man, had labour'd to infuſe into him an Hereditary Hate to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> whom he lookt on as Uſurpers of a Crown which belong'd to his Family, and us'd all poſſible means to fill his Breaſt with the Ambition of regaining his Right, and all the Heat and Courage which is neceſſary for ſo Great and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous an Enterprize.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:40321:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Dom John</hi> had indeed imbib'd the Sentiments of his Father, not to ſo high a Degree, but in ſuch a Manner as ſuited with his calm and moderate Temper. He hated the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> but not ſo as to be in pain to revenge the Injury. He had Ambition, and did not deſpair of re-aſcending the Throne of his Anceſtors; but in this He did not ſhew ſo much Impatience as Duke <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius</hi> had done; He contented himſelf with a diſtant Proſpect of a Crown, without hazarding the Repoſe of his Life, and a certain Fortune, which was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready the greateſt that could conſiſt with the Condition of a Subject.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:40321:10"/>
            <p>In ſhort, it is moſt certain, if he had been preciſely what Duke <hi>Theodoſius</hi> wiſh'd him, he had been leſs fit to obtain what he deſign'd him for. The <hi>Conde</hi> Duke obſerv'd him with ſo ſtrict an Eye, that if his manner of Living had not been entirely the Effect of his Natural Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that vigilant Miniſter would have ſoon deſcry'd it; and this muſt have been fatal to his Eaſe and Fortune. The Court of <hi>Spain</hi> would never have entruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with ſo large a Power, or ſuffer'd him to lead an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moleſted Life in the Heart of his Country.</p>
            <p>The moſt refin'd Politicks could never have taught ſo wiſe a Conduct towards the <hi>Spaniards,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:40321:10"/> as the Bent of his Genius, His Birth, his Fortunes, his Title to the Crown; but by the Laws of Politicks it is ever a Crime to be Formidable. This he knew well enough, and ſaw plainly there was but one way for him to take: and this his Inclination, as well as Reaſon, led him to. There was but one way to leſſen his Offence, and that was to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der himſelf leſs fear'd. To this end he concern'd himſelf in no manner of Buſineſs, and ſeem'd wholly bent on his Diverſion and Pleaſure. He acted very well this Part; and at <hi>Villavveioſa,</hi> the Ordinary Reſidence of the Dukes of <hi>Braganza,</hi> there was nothing but Hunting-Matches, Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and all thoſe about him
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40321:11"/> were a ſort of People proper to make the Pleaſures of a Delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Country reliſh. In ſhort; Nature and Fortune ſeem'd to conſpire; one to give him all the Qualities proper for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent State of Affairs; and the other to diſpoſe the State of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs to diſplay his Natural Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities.</p>
            <p>Theſe did not ſhine enough to give the <hi>Spaniards</hi> grounds to fear he would attempt to make himſelf King; but they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd ſolid enough for the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugueſe</hi> to hope for a mild and eaſy Government of themſelves, ſhould they re-place him on the Throne of his Anceſtors.</p>
            <p>His Conduct did not give the leaſt Jealouſy, till a certain Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40321:11"/> alarm'd the Firſt Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
            <p>The People of <hi>Evora</hi> being oppreſs'd with new Taxes, and reduc'd to Deſpair, roſe; and, in the Heat of the Tumult, ſome of their Leaders began to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim againſt the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and declare publickly for the Houſe of <hi>Braganza.</hi> This Accident made the Court ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble how much they had miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken their Intereſt, in leaving ſo Rich and Potent a Family, whoſe Rights to the Crown were ſo clear, in the midſt of a Conquer'd Country.</p>
            <p>For this Conſideration the Council of <hi>Spain</hi> reſolv'd to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Duke of <hi>Braganza,</hi> or at leaſt to ſend him out of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal.</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:40321:12"/> In the firſt place they offer'd him the Government of <hi>Milan;</hi> which he refus'd, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending his frequent Indiſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; That he had not a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Knowledge of the Affairs of <hi>Italy,</hi> to acquit himſelf in a Poſt of ſo much Difficulty and Weight.</p>
            <p>The Miniſter ſeem'd to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove his Reaſons, but look'd out for ſome other means to draw him to Court. The King's Marching to Suppreſs the Revolt in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> was the Matter which afforded the next Pretence. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Occaſion he writes to him <hi>to come at the Head of the Nobility of his Country, to join the Troops of</hi> Caſtile <hi>in ſo glorious an Expedition, where the King Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40321:12"/> in Perſon.</hi> But the Duke, who had a juſt Suſpicion of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever came from Court, ſoon diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd this Artifice, and excus'd himſelf from this Attendance; pretending, That <hi>His Birth and Quality oblig'd him to an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Expence, and his Fortunes were not in a condition to ſupport it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> were at that time engag'd in a War, and the <hi>French</hi> Fleet had been off the Coaſts of <hi>Portugal;</hi> and this Occaſion gave that Miniſter a fair Colour to cover his Deſign. It was neceſſary to appoint ſome General to Command the Forces which were deſign'd for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Coaſts, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting the <hi>French</hi> from making a Deſcent. He ſent the Duke
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40321:13"/> therefore a Commiſſion for this purpoſe, which was ſo fill'd with Compliments, and intruſted him with ſo unlimited a Power to encreaſe or make alteration in all Gariſons, and diſpoſe of Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels in the Ports at his Diſcretion, that by ſo abſolute a Confidence he ſeem'd to deliver the whole Kingdom into his hands. But this fair Appearance only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd the Snare; and at the ſame time he ſent ſecret Orders to <hi>Dom Lopez Ozono,</hi> who Commanded the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleet, to put into one of the Ports, near where the Duke ſhould happen to be, upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of being driven in by Streſs of Weather, and then to invite him to ſome Entertainment, and when he was Aboard to bring
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40321:13"/> him into <hi>Spain.</hi> But Fate order'd Matters quite otherwiſe; and the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Admiral being ſurpriz'd with a Tempeſt, loſt ſeveral of his Ships; and the reſt were ſo diſpers'd, that he could not Land with them in <hi>Portugal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ill Succeſs of this Project did not diſmay the <hi>Conde</hi> Duke; he imputed the Duke of <hi>Bragan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za</hi>'s Eſcape wholly to Chance and Fortune, concluding, That all things muſt neceſſarily have anſwer'd his Deſires, if <hi>Dom Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pez</hi> had arriv'd in the Ports of that Kingdom according to his Inſtructions. And therefore he invents a new Trick, and writes to that Prince in the moſt obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging manner he could imagine, filling his Letter with the higheſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40321:14"/> Expreſſions of Confidence, as if he had been a Partner with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the Miniſtry and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. In this Letter he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains of <hi>the Misfortune of the Fleet, and how ſenſible he was of the Loſs they had ſuſtain'd, at a Time when the Enemies were ſo For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable at Sea;</hi> That being <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily depriv'd of the Naval Strength, which ſhould have guarded their Coaſts, the King wiſh'd he would take an exact Review of all the Forts and Harbours of that Kingdom, which might he expos'd to the Inſults of the</hi> French. And with this he ſent an Order for Forty Thouſand Ducats for the defraying his Expences, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing more Forces in caſe it ſhould be needful.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:40321:14"/>
            <p>At the ſame time the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the Citadels, moſt of which were <hi>Spaniards,</hi> had ſecret Orders ſent to ſecure his Perſon, when a favourable Occaſion ſhould preſent, and ſend him into <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Braganza</hi> reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on theſe high Marks of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence; and how little agreeable this was to the uſual Conduct of that Miniſter, began to ſuſpect the Sincerity of his Intentions, which, in the end, caus'd the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to fall into that Snare which he laid for another. The Prince therefore writes back to aſſure him, That <hi>He accepted with abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Joy the Command which the King had given him;</hi> That <hi>He hoped by his Application, and Zeal
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40321:15"/> for his Service, he ſhould juſtify his Choice, and ſhew himſelf worthy of the Favour he had ſo graciouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd on him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now having a nearer Proſpect than before of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting the Throne of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, he made uſe of all the Power he was inveſted with to put his Friends into all Poſts and Employs where they might one day be uſeful to him. He ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Moneys in making of New Creatures; and when he viſited the Forts, it was always with a great Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, which made them deſpair of ſeizing his Perſon.</p>
            <p>The whole Court of <hi>Spain</hi> began to murmur that a Truſt of ſo high a nature ſhould be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40321:15"/> lodg'd in him, the King only being privy to the Reaſons of this Conduct. Every one began to rail at the <hi>Conde</hi> Duke, as Allied to the Houſe of <hi>Braganza,</hi> urging, That it was the laſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudence to make a Perſon Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the Forces in <hi>Portugal,</hi> who had ſo great Pretenſions to the Crown of that Kingdom; That this was in effect to put him in a condition to aſſert his Title, and turn his Arms againſt his Lawful Soveraign. This ſerv'd only to confirm the King in his Reſolution, who approv'd the Deſign better when he found the People did not diſcern the Secret of it. In the mean time the Duke of <hi>Braganza,</hi> by virtue of his new Employment, travers'd
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40321:16"/> all Parts of <hi>Portugal;</hi> in which Progreſs he laid the Foundations of his Reſtoration. His Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page was Magnificent, and drew the Eyes of the People where-ever he came: He heard all who came to him with great Mildneſs and Sweetneſs of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: He kept the Soldiers from committing the leaſt Diſorder; frequently extoll'd the Officers, winning them by all the Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences which were in his Power to beſtow. His free Deportment charm'd the Nobility; all whom he receiv'd with obliging Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions, according to their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Quality: In ſhort, he diſpenſed his Favours where-ever he came, and won more by Hopes of future Benefits than
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40321:16"/> preſent; and all who were about him began to eſteem it the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Happineſs could befal them, that ſo noble a Prince ſhould be reſtor'd to the Throne.</p>
            <p>The Party who adhered to his Intereſt, omitted nothing which might conduce to establiſh his Reputation. Among theſe, none labour'd more effectually than <hi>Pinto Ribeuro,</hi> Comptroller of his Houſhold, to ſet all Machines on work, and form a Scheme for the Advancement of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. This Man had all the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities proper for a Buſineſs of this nature; He was Active, Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, had great Experience in Buſineſs, and a violent Paſſion for the Reſtoration of the Duke; doubtleſs flattering himſelf with
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40321:17"/> the Hopes of having a large ſhare in the Miniſtry whenever he ſhould bring this to paſs. The Prince had in private aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd him, That he would lay hold of any Fair occaſion to place himſelf in the Throne, but was reſolv'd not to hazard this at all Adventures, as a Man who had nothing to loſe; that he might manage the People, and Gain as many Creatures as he could, provided himſelf did not appear to have any ſhare in what he did.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pinto</hi> had for a long time la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd with great Induſtry to obſerve who were diſaffected, and to encreaſe the Number. For this purpoſe he privately rais'd Murmurs againſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40321:17"/> Government, ſometimes railing againſt the Government with a great deal of Warmth, at other times with more Reſerve, according to the Character or Humour of the Perſons he was with. He would frequently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mind People of Quality of the Honourable Poſts their Families had formerly enjoy'd when <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal</hi> was govern'd by its Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Princes. But nothing exaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated the Nobility more, than the Summons which the King had ſent them to attend him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Catalonia. Pinto</hi> inveighed againſt this Expedition, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting it as a <hi>ſort of Baniſhment;</hi> urging, That <hi>they muſt not hope to return without great difficulties;</hi> That <hi>beſides a vaſt Expence, they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40321:18"/> muſt endure the hateful Inſolence of the</hi> Spaniards; That <hi>The Court of</hi> Spain <hi>had a private Intereſt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Braveſt Men, or expoſe them in all Places where there was moſt Danger, and leaſt Glory to be obtain'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If he happened to be among Citizens or Merchants, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim'd againſt the Injuſtice of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who had ruin'd <hi>Lisbon</hi> and the whole Country of <hi>Portugal,</hi> by transferring the Trade of the <hi>Indies</hi> to <hi>Cadiz;</hi> he entertain'd them with nothing elſe but Diſcourſes of the extreme Miſery they were reduc'd to by ſo Tyrannical a Government; extolling the <hi>Hollanders</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talonians,</hi> who had nobly deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd themſelves. In the laſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40321:18"/> place, he ſuggeſted to the Clergy how they had violated the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges and Immunities of the Church: That the moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Dignities and Benefices, which ought to be a Recompence to the Merit and Capacity af the <hi>Portugueſe,</hi> were bcome a Prey to Foreigners.</p>
            <p>In Company of thoſe whom he knew to be diſaffected, he would ever turn his Diſcourſe to his Maſter's Humour and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Living. Here he would complain of that Idle Life in which he ſeem'd to be buried, expreſſing his great Regret, that the only Perſon who was able to remedy their Grievances, ſhould ſhew ſo little Affection to his Country, or Concern for his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40321:19"/> and obſerving theſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes to make an impreſſion on them, he puſh'd Matters ſo far, as to flatter ſome with the Glorious Title of the Aſſerters of the Liberty of their Country, raiſing their indignation at the ill treatment of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and to give other Hopes of advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing their Fortunes by a Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, he manag'd the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the People with ſo great Skill, that being well aſſur'd of Divers privately, he procur'd a Meeting of the Nobility, with the Archbiſhop of <hi>Lisbon</hi> at their Head.</p>
            <p>This Prelate was deſcended of one of the beſt Houſes<note n="*" place="bottom">D' Acugna.</note> in that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40321:19"/> Kingdom; was a Man of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, an able Stateſman, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd by the People, but hated by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> whom he hated no leſs, becauſe they had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd the Archbiſhop of <hi>Braga,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Dom Sebaſtian de Mattos de Noroguia.</note> a Creature of the Vice-queen, whom they had made Preſident of the Chamber of <hi>Opaco,</hi> and given a ſhare in the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Affairs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dom Miguel d' Almeida</hi> was one of the moſt cOnſiderable Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of this Company. This was a venerable Old Gentleman, who had gain'd a mighty Eſteem by his Worth: He plac'd his Glory in preferring the Intereſt of his Country to his Fortunes, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40321:20"/> could not without Indignation ſee it enſlav'd by Uſurpers. He perſiſted in this ſenſe his whole Life with great Bravery and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and neither the Advice of his Friends, or the Intreaties of his Relations could ever induce him to go to the Palace, or make his Court to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. This Steddineſs in his Conduct had created ſome Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſy of him, and determin'd <hi>Pinto</hi> to pitch on him to make his Declaration to, being well aſſur'd he ſhould not hazard any thing in making a Confidence with a Man of ſuch a Character, and one who was able to bring ſo great a Number of the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity over to his Party.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:40321:20"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Dom Antonio d' Almada,</hi> an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate Friend to the Archbiſhop was there, and <hi>Dom Lewis</hi> his Son; <hi>Dom Lewis d' Acugna,</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew to that Prelate, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to the Daughter of <hi>Dom An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio d' Almada,</hi> the Maſter of the Horſe; <hi>Mello, Dom George</hi> his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; <hi>Pedro Mendoza, Dom Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drigo de Saa,</hi> High Chamberlain, and divers Officers of the Royal Family, whoſe Place were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come empty Title, ſince <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal</hi> had loſt her Natural Kings.</p>
            <p>At this Meeting the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, who was naturally Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, diſplay'd the calamitous State of that Kingdom; He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to them, <hi>How</hi> Philip <hi>the Second, to ſecure his Conqueſt, had deſtroy'd an infinite Number of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40321:21"/> the Nobility:</hi> That <hi>He had not ſpared the Church, witneſs the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Brief of Abſolution</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſtagio.</note> 
               <hi>which he had obtain'd of the Pope for the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Two thouſand Prieſts and Religious perſons, whom he had put to Death to ſecure his Uſurpation:</hi> That <hi>ſince thoſe Diſmal Times, the</hi> Spaniards <hi>had not changed their Meaſures:</hi> That <hi>they had taken off a great many Worthy perſons for no other Crime, but their Love to their Country:</hi> That <hi>no Man preſent had his Life or Eſtate ſecure to him:</hi> That <hi>the Great Men were excluded from the Government, deſtitute of Employ, and neglected:</hi> That <hi>the Church had been fill'd with a ſcandalous Clergy, ſince</hi> Vaſconcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40321:21"/> 
               <hi>had beſtow'd Benefices as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards on his Creatures:</hi> That <hi>the People were oppreſs'd with Taxes; the Country wanted Hands to Till it, and the Cities were deſolate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exhauſted by thoſe Forces which were ſent into</hi> Catalonia: That <hi>theſe Orders to Summon the Nobility under a Pretence, of attending the King, was the laſt ſhift the Miniſter could uſe to take off the Remains of thoſe Gentlemen whom he conceiv'd might be an Obſtacle to his pernicious Deſigns:</hi> That <hi>the leaſt Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune which could befal them, muſt be a tedious Baniſhment, and they muſt wear away their Lives in the Heart of</hi> Caſtile, <hi>while new Colonies were poſſeſs'd of their Eſtates at Home:</hi> That <hi>for his part, in this deplorable ſtate of Things, he ſhould
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40321:22"/> chuſe to dye, rather than ſee the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Ruin and Deſtruction of his Country, if he had not ſome Hopes of ſo many Worthy Perſons were not met together to no purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Speech reviv'd in the Company the uneaſy Memory of thoſe Grievances they had ſo long labour'd under. Every one was earneſt to give ſome Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Cruelties of <hi>Vaſconcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los;</hi> Some had loſt their Eſtates by his Injuſtice, others had been turn'd out of their Hereditary Places and Governments to make room for his Creatures; divers of them had for a long time groan'd in Priſon to ſatisfy the Jealouſy of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Miniſters; ſome were concern'd for the Loſs
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40321:22"/> for their Fathers, Brothers, Friends detain'd at <hi>Madrid,</hi> or ſent into <hi>Catalonia</hi> as Hoſtages for the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity of their Countrymen. In ſhort, there was no one in this publick Cauſe who had not ſome private Injury to revenge. The Expedition into <hi>Catalonia</hi> incens'd them, and rais'd their Indignation to the laſt degree. They ſaw plainly this did not proceed from any Neceſſity, which conſtrain'd the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to make uſe of their Aſſiſtance, but a deſign of that Court to ruin them by ſo long a March. Theſe Conſiderations, joyn'd with the Hopes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging ſo many Affronts as they had receiv'd, determin'd them, and made them reſolve to take all proper Meaſures to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40321:23"/> throw off a Yoke which they ſound too heavy to bear; and being depriv'd of all Hopes of mitigating their unhappy Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they reproach'd their Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence as a Baſeneſs and Meanneſs of Spirit, and unanimouſly agreed there was a neceſſity of driving out the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> but were divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded what Form of Government they ought to prefer.</p>
            <p>One part of the Company were for a Republick, like that of <hi>Holland;</hi> another part were inclin'd to have a King; and of this Number ſome propos'd the Duke of <hi>Braganza,</hi> others the Marqueſs <hi>de Villareal,</hi> and others the Duke <hi>d' Aveiro,</hi> all three Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Royal Blood of <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal,</hi> each delivering his Mind as
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40321:23"/> his Fancy or Intereſt led him. But the Archbiſhop, who was devoted to the Houſe of <hi>Bragan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za,</hi> dextrouſly uſing the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his Character, made a Remonſtrance, not without ſome Vehemence; alledging, That <hi>the Choice of Government was not Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary:</hi> That <hi>they could not in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience break that Oath of Fidelity which they had taken to</hi> Spain, <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it were to do Juſtice to the Rightful Heir of that Crown, which all the World knew was the Duke of</hi> Braganza; <hi>and therefore they muſt reſolve to acknowledge him as their King; or for ever remain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Dominion of</hi> Spain. In the next place he deſir'd them to reflect on <hi>the Power, the great Wealth, and the vaſt Number of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40321:24"/> Vaſſals of that Prince, on whom one Third of that Kingdom depended;</hi> urging, <hi>They could never hope to drive out the</hi> Spaniards, <hi>unleſs they had him at their Head; and that to engage him in an Affair of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, they muſt offer him the Crown, whoſe Right was indubitable, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt Prince of the Blood.</hi> From thence he paſs'd to his good Qualities, extolling his <hi>Prudence, Wiſdom,</hi> and eſpecially the <hi>ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Temper,</hi> and his <hi>obliging Behaviour.</hi> In ſhort, he gave ſo happy a Turn to this Matter, they all declar'd for him as their King, and agreed, That nothing ſhould be wanting that could engage him in this Deſign. Thus the Company broke up, having firſt agreed on the Time and Place
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40321:24"/> where they ſhould meet again, to conſider of the beſt Means to bring the Matter to a ſpeedy and ſucceſsful Iſſue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pinto</hi> ſeeing them thus diſpos'd in Favour of his Maſter, writ privately to him to come into the Neighbourhood of <hi>Lisbon,</hi> for the encouraging the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators by his Preſence, and taking preciſe Meaſures with them for the Execution of that Deſign. This crafty Man put in Motion all the Wheels in that Affair, without appearing to be any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther concern'd than a private Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, acted by a Zeal for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Service. He ſeem'd to doubt whether his Maſter would enter into it, upon the Account of his Natural Averſion to all Hazard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40321:25"/> Undertakings, which require Application and Attendance. He ſtarted ſome Difficulties, which ſerv'd only to remove all Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of any Underſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and his Maſter; and yet were ſuch as tended rather to excite their Ardour, than diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them.</p>
            <p>Upon the Advice which <hi>Pinto</hi> gave, the Duke ſome Days af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter left <hi>Villa-vicioſa,</hi> and came to <hi>Almada,</hi> a Caſtle near <hi>Lisbon,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Colour of Viſiting the Forts of that Kingdom. His Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page was very Magnificent, and he had a vaſt Train, compos'd of Men of Quality, and Officers of the Army; which more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembl'd a King taking Poſſeſſion of his Kingdom, than of a Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40321:25"/> of a Province viſiting the Places under his Care and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection. Being near <hi>Lisbon,</hi> he could not diſpenſe with paying his Duty to the Vice-Queen. When he enter'd the Great Court of the Palace, all the Avenues were fill'd with an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of People, who crowded to ſee him paſs along, and moſt of the Nobility came to his Houſe to wait on him. It was a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Holy-day throughout the Town, and all People were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd to ſee him; there ſeem'd only to want a Herald to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim him King, or Reſolution enough in himſelf to put the Crown on his Head.</p>
            <p>But this Prince was too wiſe, and had too much Experience
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40321:26"/> to truſt ſo important a Concern to the Sallies of a fickle and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant Multitude; He very well underſtood the vaſt difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween thoſe vain Shouts which the People ſoon quit, and thoſe ſteddy Motions which are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to ſupport an Enterprize of that nature. Thus after he had taken his Leave of the Vice-Queen, he retir'd to <hi>Almada,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out going to <hi>Braganza</hi>-Houſe, or paſſing through the City, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent making the <hi>Spaniards</hi> unea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, who were already too much alarm'd at the Tranſports of the People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pinto</hi> did not fail to obſerve to his Friends the Fear and Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which his Maſter us'd; urging, That they ought to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40321:26"/> the opportunity of his ſtay at <hi>Almada,</hi> to break the Matter to him, and uſe ſome ſort of Violence to engage him to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the Crown, which was at this time abſolutely neceſſary for the publick Good. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators approving this Advice, appointed him to obtain of his Maſter ſome favourable Occaſion for making this Propoſition: He accepted this Commiſſion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out much difficulty, and the Duke of <hi>Braganza</hi> agreed to an Interview, on condition that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Three of the Conſpirators ſhould meet him, not judging it proper to explain himſelf to more.</p>
            <p>So <hi>Miguel d' Almeida, Antonio d' Almada,</hi> and <hi>Mendoza,</hi> came to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40321:27"/> him that Night; and being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduc'd privately into his Cloſet, <hi>d' Almada,</hi> who ſpoke for the reſt, made a lively Repreſentation of <hi>the unhappy State of that Kingdom, where perſons of all Conditions were expos'd to the Injuſtice and Cruelty of the</hi> Caſtillians; adding, That <hi>himſelf, with all his Greatneſs, was not ſecure from their Attempts:</hi> That <hi>He was too diſcerning a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon not to obſerve the Induſtry which the prime Miniſter us'd to deſtroy him:</hi> That <hi>there was no other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge to eſcape his ill deſigns, except the Throne:</hi> That <hi>in order to put him into that, he had Commiſſion to offer him the Services of a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Number of Perſons of Rank, who would ſacrifice their Lives and Fortunes with pleaſure for his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40321:27"/> and to deliver their Country from its inſolent Maſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place he told him, <hi>The Time of</hi> Charles <hi>the Fifth and</hi> Philip <hi>the Second were paſt, when the</hi> Spaniards <hi>were the Terror of</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, <hi>and gave Laws to their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours:</hi> That <hi>this Monarchy which had formerly conceiv'd ſuch vaſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, could now ſcarce preſerve her ancient Territory, was attack'd, and often beat by the</hi> French <hi>and</hi> Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers: That Catalonia <hi>alone employ'd her utmoſt Strength:</hi> That <hi>ſhe, was deſtitute of Troops and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and govern'd by a weak Prince, who himſelf was govern'd by a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter hateful to the Kingdom.</hi> He wiſh'd him to conſider <hi>the Alliance and Protection which he might expect from thoſe Princes, in</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:40321:28"/> Europe, <hi>who were Eternal Enemies to the Houſe of</hi> Auſtria: That Holland <hi>and</hi> Catalonia <hi>ſhew'd what Aſſiſtance he might expect from a great Miniſter,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">The Cardinal <hi>Richelieu.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>whoſe mighty Genius ſeem'd bent to ruin that Houſe:</hi> That <hi>the Sea open'd a way for receiving all neceſſary Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies.</hi> In ſhort; That <hi>the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom being empried of the</hi> Caſtillian <hi>Gariſons, which the King had been forc'd to draw out of</hi> Portugal, <hi>to encreaſe his Army in</hi> Catalonia, <hi>he could never hope for a more fovour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Juncture to aſſert his Right, and free his Country from Tyranny and Slavery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may eaſily be thought this Diſcourſe was very well reliſh'd
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40321:28"/> by the Duke of <hi>Braganza;</hi> but he with that Coldneſs, which was natural to him, ſo order'd the Expreſſions of his Reply to the Deputies, that he ſeem'd neither to leſſen or encreaſe their Hopes.</p>
            <p>He told them, That <hi>he was of their Opinion:</hi> That <hi>the</hi> Spaniards <hi>had reduc'd the Kingdom to a Deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable State:</hi> That <hi>Himſelf was not exempt from Danger:</hi> That <hi>he could never enough commend their Zeal for their Country;</hi> And that <hi>he was in particular very much oblig'd to them for the favourable Regard they had to his Intereſt: but after all, he doubted if the Time was yet come, to think of ſuch violent Remedies as they propos'd, which always had very bad conſequences, if the Event did not fall out as was projected.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:40321:29"/>
            <p>To this Anſwer (for a more poſitive one he would not give) he added ſo many Careſſes and obliging Thanks to each Man in particular, that they went away ſatisfy'd their Meſſage was well Receiv'd; but that they muſt expect the Prince would make no more Advances in the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, than by giving his Conſent when Things ſhould be in a Condition to put the Succeſs out of doubt.</p>
            <p>After the Deputies were gone, he agreed with <hi>Pinto</hi> what new Meaſures were beſt to be taken, and ſo went back to <hi>Villa-vicioſa;</hi> and now he began to feel a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet of Mind, which hinder'd him from reliſhing the Pleaſures of a private Life.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:40321:29"/>
            <p>As ſoon as he was return'd, he communicated to the Ducheſs, his Wife, the Propoſitions which had been made to him. This Princeſs was of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Extracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Siſter to the Duke of <hi>Medina Sidonia,</hi> a Grandee of <hi>Spain,</hi> and Governor of <hi>Andalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia.</hi> She had by Nature a ſtrong inclination to whatever was great and noble, which in time was grown up to a boundleſs Paſſion for Glory. The Old Duke find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mighty things were to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from her Wit and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, had taken care to improve the Gifts of Nature by a ſuitable Education. He plac'd about her the fitteſt Perſons to inſpire Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition into her Breaſt, which the World regards as ſomething no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:40321:30"/> and the chief Virtue of a Prince. She learnt ſeveral Tongues with a great deal of eaſe, but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could come near that won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous Sweetneſs with which ſhe expreſs'd her ſelf in her natural Language. In the Sound of her Voice, and in every word ſhe ſpoke, was a ſecret Charm, which raviſh'd all who heard her. Her Air was noble, great, and free, full of a majeſtick Sweetneſs, which at the ſame time inſpir'd Love and Reſpect into thoſe who were about her.</p>
            <p>She took the <hi>Portugueſe</hi> Air with ſo much eaſe, ſhe ſeem'd Born at <hi>Lisbon.</hi> In the firſt place, ſhe was careful to win the Eſteem of her Husband, which ſhe perfectly well did by the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40321:30"/> Auſterity of her Life, by a ſolid Devotion, and a perfect Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance to his Reliſh. She wav'd thoſe Pleaſures which are the ordinary Amuſement of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of her Quality and Age, and ſeem'd to employ her leiſure Hours in thoſe things which might embelliſh her Mind, or improve her Judgment.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Braganza</hi> was tranſported with the Happineſs of enjoying ſo finiſh'd a Woman: He had an infinite Eſteem for her, and an entire Confidence in her: He never undertook any thing without conſulting with her, and therefore had a care not to engage in an Affair of this kind without her Advice and Opinion.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:40321:31"/>
            <p>He diſcover'd to her the Plan of the Conſpiracy, the Names of the Perſons privy to it, their Zeal and Warmth, and every Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular that had paſs'd at <hi>Lisbon,</hi> and the Conference at <hi>Almada.</hi> He added, That on the News of the Expedition into <hi>Catalonia,</hi> he plainly ſaw the Nobility would revolt, rather than be compell'd to leave their Country: That, it was to be fear'd, upon his Refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, they would look out for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Head: That notwithſtanding, he could not forbear confeſſing, that the Danger of the Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize ſtartled him: That as oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en as he had thought of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign at a diſtance, the flattering Idea of Greatneſs had made an agreeable impreſſion on his
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:40321:31"/> Mind; but now he was upon the point of putting this in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, and running all the Risks of ſo hazardous an Undertaking, he could not look without Dread on the Danger which he and his whole Family was about to throw himſelf into. That the fickle Humour of the Multitude was not much to be rely'd on, the Edge of whoſe Courage is taken off by the leaſt Difficulty, and they eaſily diſpers'd by every Blaſt of Wind. That it was not ſufficient for him to have the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility on his ſide, unleſs they were ſupported by the Great Men of the Kingdom, but very far from hoping they would come over to his Intereſt. He could not but foreſee they would be
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:40321:32"/> the moſt cruel of his Enemies; the natural Pride of Mankind never ſuffering them to make a Maſter of one who has once been their Equal.</p>
            <p>Theſe Conſiderations, with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other; as the Power of <hi>Spain,</hi> the ſmall Aſſurance of Foreign Aſſiſtance, ballanc'd his Paſſion for Government. But the Ducheſs, who had a greater Firmneſs of Mind, and a more lively Ambition, clos'd wholly with the Conſpiracy. The View of ſo great an Undertaking, ſerv'd only to excite her Courage, and rowſe up her Ardent Thirſt after Greatneſs: She repreſented to her Husband with a great deal of Vehemence, <hi>the undoubted Rights which he had to the Crown:</hi> That
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40321:32"/> 
               <hi>in the deplorable State to which the</hi> Caſtillians <hi>had reduc'd</hi> Portugal, <hi>a Man of his Rank and Quality could not diſpenſe with remaining any longer indifferent:</hi> That <hi>his Children and Poſterity would reproach his Memory with a Puſillanimity beneath his Blood, if he ſhould loſe ſo favourable an Opportunity.</hi> After this ſhe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aggerated to that Prince <hi>the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Reigning in a Country where he could not Obey without Fear; the Charms of a Crown, and the Facility of ſeizing it:</hi> That <hi>in caſe he ſhould miſs of that Foreign Aid which had been offer'd to him, he was Potent enough to expel the</hi> Spaniards, <hi>eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially at this Juncture, when there was a Revolt in</hi> Catalonia. In fine, ſhe ſo Skilfully ſhew'd him the Crown on its moſt glittering
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40321:33"/> ſide, that ſhe determin'd him. But in this ſhe agreed with him, to let the Number of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators encreaſe, before he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd himſelf more poſitively, and not to appear publickly in this Matter till the Moment of its Execution.</p>
            <p>All this while the Court was not without ſome Diſquiet. The extraordinary Marks of Joy which the People of <hi>Lisbon</hi> had ſhewn on the Duke of <hi>Braganza</hi>'s ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing amongſt them, had made a great Impreſſion on the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. He began to ſuſpect pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Clubs were held in that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and ſome Rumours, which commonly precede great Events, exceedingly encreas'd his uneaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:40321:33"/>
            <p>The King held ſeveral Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils on this Occaſion; in which it was reſolv'd, That for the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual defeating the <hi>Portugueſe</hi> Hopes of a Revolt, the Duke of <hi>Braganza,</hi> the only Perſon whom they had occaſion to fear, ſhould forthwith be ſent for to <hi>Madrid.</hi> For this purpoſe the <hi>Conde</hi> Duke ſent a Courier to him, with this Meſſage; That <hi>the King had a Mind to be inform'd from himſelf, and confer with him concerning the State of the Troops and Gariſons in</hi> Portugal: That <hi>he was mightily wiſh'd for at Court by his Friends; and that he could not doubt he ſhould be receiv'd in a manner ſuitable to his Birth and Merit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No Clap of Thunder could have ſurpriz'd him more than
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:40321:34"/> this News. The Earneſtneſs and different Pretences they made uſe of to draw him out of <hi>Portugal,</hi> confirm'd his ſuſpicion they had a Deſign on his Perſon, and were reſolv'd to take him off. They had left pretended Employs and falſe Careſſes, and were now come to poſitive Orders, which would ſoon be follow'd by Force and Violence in caſe of Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. This put him into a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick Fear, imagining he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd; the uſual Fate of thoſe who have great Projects in their Head, who ſtill believe the World is buſy in obſerving their Steps, and gueſſes at the Secret of them. Thus did that diffident Prince perplex himſelf, thinking he was now plung'd in an Ocean of Trouble.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:40321:34"/>
            <p>However, to gain Time, and have leiſure to give the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators notice of his Danger, by the Advice of his Wife, he ſent a Gentleman of his Houſe, a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of great Addreſs and Fidelity, to <hi>Madrid,</hi> to aſſure the Miniſter he would ſuddenly attend the King. To this Man he gave ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Inſtructions, to invent from Time to Time different Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to excuſe his Delay, hoping to prevent the Storm by bringing the Conſpiracy to ripeneſs. As ſoon as this Gentleman was at <hi>Madrid,</hi> he aſſur'd the King and Firſt Miniſter, that his Maſter follow'd him. He took a great Houſe, which he furniſh'd very richly, and retain'd a great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Servants, giving them Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:40321:35"/> by way of Advance, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out very conſiderable Sums of Money every day. In ſhort, he omitted nothing to make them believe the Prince would come immediately, and appear at Court in all the Splendor becoming a Perſon of his Rank.</p>
            <p>Some few Days after, he feign'd to have receiv'd Advice, That he was very ill. At laſt, finding this would not hold longer, he preſented a Memorial to the Firſt Miniſter, praying in the Name of the Duke his Maſter, the King would aſſign his Precedence in the Court.</p>
            <p>He thought this would take up ſome time to adjuſt, and meet with Oppoſition from the Great Men, who would inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vene
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:40321:35"/> to maintain their Rights: But the Miniſter, who began to ſuſpect theſe Delays, ſoon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd all Difficulties, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd the King to declare in his Favour, in every point for his Honour; ſo deſirous he was to draw him out of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and ſee him at <hi>Madrid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Conſpirators no ſooner underſtood the Orders which the Duke had receiv'd from the Court, but fearing he ſhould obey them they ſent <hi>Mendoza</hi> to confirm him and engage him more ſtrictly to their Party. They made choice of this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, becauſe being Governor of a Place near <hi>Villa-vicioſa,</hi> the pretence of going to his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment covered the ſecret Intention
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40321:36"/> of this Journey from the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards.</hi> He took an opportunity of meeting that Prince a Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; They ſtruck into the Wood, and ſtopping in a private place, <hi>Mendoza</hi> laid before him <hi>the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger which he expos'd himſelf to by go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Court:</hi> That <hi>he would abſolutely ruin the Hopes of the Nobility and People by putting himſelf with too raſh a confidence into the Hands of his Enemies:</hi> That <hi>there were a great Number of well-qualified Gentlemen who were reſolv'd to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice their Lives and Fortunes for his Service:</hi> That <hi>they only expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed notice from him when they ſhould appear:</hi> That <hi>the Critical minute was now come when he muſt chuſe either to dye or wear a Crown:</hi> That <hi>it was Hazardous to make any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:40321:36"/> Delays; and he muſt not doubt an Affair of ſo great Importance, which was entruſted in ſo many Hands, muſt needs at length come to the Knowledge of the</hi> Spaniards. The Duke reply'd, That <hi>he was of his mind, and that he might aſſure his Friends that he was reſolv'd to put himſelf at their Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mendoza</hi> return'd Poſt to <hi>Liſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon,</hi> acquainted his Friends with the Succeſs of his Voyage; and that the Prince deſir'd <hi>Pinto</hi> might come to him. Him they ſent away inſtantly with neceſſary In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions to inform the Duke of the Scheme and Ways by which they intended to put their Project in Execution. When <hi>Pinto</hi> came, he acquainted him in what Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion the Court at <hi>Lisbon</hi> was;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:40321:37"/> the Vice-Queen made high Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of the Inſolence and Pride of <hi>Vaſconcellos;</hi> That ſhe could not any longer endure that all the Diſpatches from <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould be Addreſs'd to him, while ſhe being inveſted with a glittering Title, had no real Authority. This Complaint was the more to be regarded, becauſe That Princeſs was a Perſon of great Merit, and every way capable of Diſcharging the Extent of her Truſt: but indeed the Greatneſs of her Genius, and her other good Qualities, were the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Reaſon why ſhe had ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable a ſhare in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment allow'd her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pinto</hi> obſerv'd to his Maſter how much this miſunderſtanding
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:40321:37"/> favour'd his Deſigns, and that he could not lay hold of a fairer occaſion than theſe Diviſions at Court, which would not give the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Miniſters leave to obſerve the Steps he ſhould take.</p>
            <p>The Duke, who perceiv'd the Strength of his Reaſons, found himſelf likewiſe preſs'd by that Gentleman whom he ſent to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid.</hi> He receiv'd Letters from him every Day, aſſuring him, That he could not find new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours for his Abſence, or delude the Miniſter, who would not any longer hear his Excuſes. Thus ſeeing he had no Time to loſe, he reſolv'd to riſe without delay. And now to gain Time for the diſpoſing his Affairs, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:40321:38"/> his Agent to repreſent to the <hi>Conde</hi> Duke <hi>d'Olivarez,</hi> That he ſhould have been at <hi>Madrid</hi> before that time, if he had had Money enough to bear the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences of his Journey, and enable him to make a Figure ſuitable to his Quality and Character; and that as ſoon as he could raiſe the neceſſary Funds, he would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly come away for the Court.</p>
            <p>When he had ſent the Diſpatch, he took <hi>Pinto</hi> with him into the Ducheſſes Apartment, to conſider of the moſt proper means to put their Deſign in execution. And after ſome Debate, the Duke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd on this, That <hi>it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſecure</hi> Lisbon, <hi>which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Capital, was the Spring which mov'd the whole Kingdom:</hi> That <hi>on
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:40321:38"/> the ſame Day that City ſhould declare for him, he would cauſe himſelf to be proclaim'd King of</hi> Portugal <hi>in all the Cities of his Dependance:</hi> That <hi>thoſe of his Friends, who were Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of Forts, ſhould do the ſame in all Places where they Commanded, and the Conſpirators ſhould raiſe the People in all the Towns and Villages which belong'd to them; that ſo this General Inſurrection diffuſing it ſelf like a Conflagration through every part of the Kingdom, the</hi> Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards <hi>might not know whither to bend their Arms:</hi> That <hi>he would fling his own Regiment into the Town of</hi> Elvas, <hi>the Governor of which was at his Devotion:</hi> That <hi>as for the manner of ſeizing</hi> Lisbon, <hi>he could not preſcribe any thing, that Action depending wholly on the Time, and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:40321:39"/> other Circumſtances when they ſhould attempt it:</hi> That <hi>however he was of the Opinion, they ought to make their firſt Attacks on the Palace, and ſecure the Perſon of the Vice-Queen, and the reſt of the</hi> Spaniards, <hi>who might ſerve as Hoſtages for the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render of the Citadel, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe might very much incommode the Town after they were Maſters of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He gave two Letters of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, one to <hi>d'Almeida,</hi> and the other to <hi>Mendoza;</hi> in which he ſignify'd to them, That he had entruſted the Bearer with his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions; He only added, That he hop'd they would be Faithful to the Aſſurances they had given him, and act with Courage and Vigour in the Work they were
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:40321:39"/> about to undertake. After this the Duke ſent <hi>Pinto</hi> to <hi>Lisbon,</hi> having firſt given him the higheſt Marks of Confidence, he ſhould enjoy the ſame Place in his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, after a Revolution, that he now had.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as he came to <hi>Lisbon,</hi> he deliver'd his Letters to <hi>d' Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meida</hi> and <hi>Mendoza,</hi> who ſent im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to <hi>Le Mos</hi> and <hi>Coreé,</hi> whom <hi>Pinto</hi> had formerly brought over to his Maſter's Intereſt. Theſe were two Rich Citizens, who had a mighty Authority with the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; they had paſs'd through moſt of the Offices of the City, and had a great Number of Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men who depended on them. Theſe Men had taken a great deal of Pains to foment and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:40321:40"/> in the Minds of the Townſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men an Averſion to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> by Rumors they daily ſpread of Taxes intended to be rais'd the beginning of the next Year. They had diſcharg'd ſeveral of their Workmen, eſpecially the moſt Mutinous, pretending the Badneſs of Trade would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to employ them, they could not keep them any longer; while their Real Intent was by Neceſſity and Starving, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them for an Inſurrection. And the better to accompliſh their Ends, they ſupply'd theſe ſtarving Wretches from Time to Time, keeping them at their Devotion. Beſides this, theſe Men held a private Correſpondence with the principal Perſons in all Parts of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:40321:40"/> the Town; by the help of which, they aſſur'd the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators, That upon notice given the Night before the Execution, they would engage to raiſe the People at any Hour they ſhould aſſign.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pinto</hi> being thus aſſur'd of the Inferior People, began to look to the other Conſpirators, whom he urg'd to be ready upon the firſt Alarm, deſiring they would ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure their Friends under pretence of ſome private Quarrel, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making them privy to the deſign in which they ſhould be employ'd. In this Conduct he gave proof of an Extraordinary Prudence, there being abundance of People who have Courage and Reſolution when the Sword
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:40321:41"/> is in their hands, who are not able in cold Blood to bear the weight of ſo important a Secret.</p>
            <p>Thus finding every one firm, undaunted, and impatient to be reveng'd on the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd with <hi>d' Almeida, Mendoza d' Almada,</hi> and <hi>Mello;</hi> who find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all things in ſuch a condition as they wiſh'd, agreed on <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">1ſt. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1640.</note> the Firſt of <hi>December</hi> for the Execution. They gave notice to the Duke of <hi>Braganza</hi> of this Reſolve, that ſo he might cauſe himſelf to be proclaim'd King in the Province of <hi>Alenteio,</hi> which almoſt entirely depended on him; and agreed before the Company broke up, to have another Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:40321:41"/>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">25th of <hi>November.</hi>
               </note> to take the laſt Meaſures for the Action.</p>
            <p>The 25th of <hi>November,</hi> at night, they met at <hi>Braganza</hi> Houſe, as they had agreed. They found they could account on a hundred and fifty Gentlemen, the moſt part of which were the Heads of their Families, with all their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticks, and about Two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Citizens and Tradeſmen; and they concluded by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of theſe, they ſhould bring the greateſt Part of the People over to them.</p>
            <p>The Death of <hi>Vaſconcellos</hi> was reſolv'd on as a Victim due to the Reſentment of the <hi>Portugueſe,</hi> and ſome propos'd to treat the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:40321:42"/> Archbiſhop of <hi>Braga</hi> after the ſame manner. They repreſented him as a Man whoſe great Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties render'd him formidable: That it was not to be thought he could ſtand as an unconcern'd Spectator in this publick Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: That poſſibly he might put himſelf at the Head of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,</hi> and their Creatures; and whilſt they were buſy in making themſelves Maſters of the Palace, he might throw himſelf into the Citadel, or come to the Aſſiſtance of the Vice-Queen, to whom all the World knew he was devoted: That in an Affair of this Nature it was a great Imprudence to leave Enemies behind them: That ſuch a Conduct might poſſibly give them occaſion to repent ſeverely
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:40321:42"/> of their ill-tim'd and miſtaken Pity.</p>
            <p>Theſe Reaſons drew the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of the Company to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to his Death; and this Prelate had ſuffer'd the ſame Fate as <hi>Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concelles,</hi> if <hi>Dom Miguel d' Almeida</hi> had not taken his part. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated to the Conſpirators, That <hi>the Death of a Man of his Character, and in ſo high a Dignity, would render them odious to all the World:</hi> That <hi>ſuch an Action would draw on the Duke of</hi> Braganza <hi>the Hatred of the Clergy and Inquiſition, a Race of Men formidable to the greateſt Princes, and add the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of an Excommunicated Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to that of Rebel and Uſurper:</hi> That <hi>the Prince himſelf would be deeply affected to ſee his Acceſſion to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:40321:43"/> the Throne blemiſh'd by ſo bloody an Action:</hi> That <hi>Himſelf would have an Eye over him, and take effectual care to prevent his undertaking any thing to the prejudice of the publick Intereſt.</hi> In ſhort, he ſpoke ſo much in his Favour, that he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd the Life of that Prelate, of his Friends, who could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe any thing to a Man of his Worth.</p>
            <p>Nothing farther remain'd to be adjuſted, but the Order they ſhould march in, and the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of making the firſt Attack. At laſt it was reſolv'd to throw themſelves in four different Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, into ſo many ſeveral Parts of the Palace, and make themſelves Maſters of the ſeveral Avenues; to cut off all Communication, and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:40321:43"/> prevent the <hi>Spaniards</hi> from bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Aſſiſtance. That <hi>Dom Miguel d' Almeida</hi> ſhould attack the <hi>German</hi> Guard before the Palace-Gates: That the Great Maſter of the Horſe, <hi>Mello,</hi> his Brother, and <hi>Dom Eſtean d' Acugna</hi> at the Head of the Townſmen, ſhould ſurprize a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Company which kept Guard every Day before the Fort: That <hi>Feillo de Menezes, Ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel Saa,</hi> the Great Chamberlain, ſhould make themſelves Maſters of <hi>Vaſconcello</hi>'s Apartment, whom they ſhould forthwith diſpatch: That <hi>Dom Antonio d' Almada, Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doza, Dom Carlos Norogna,</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio de Salſania,</hi> ſhould ſecure the Perſon of the Vice-Queen, and all the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in the Palace to ſerve as Hoſtages if there ſhould be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion:
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:40321:44"/> That whilſt each one was buſy in making themſelves Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Poſts, aſſign'd them ſome few Horſe ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tach'd away, who, with ſome prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Citizens ſhould proclaim <hi>Dom John</hi> Duke of <hi>Braganza,</hi> King of <hi>Portugal:</hi> That when the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude was drawn into the Streets, they ſhould throw themſelves where any Oppoſition ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be made. Thus they broke up with a Reſolution to meet on <hi>Saturday</hi> the Firſt of <hi>December,</hi> ſome at <hi>Dom Miguel d' Almeida</hi>'s, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers at <hi>d' Almada</hi>'s and <hi>Mendoza</hi>'s Houſes, where the Conſpirators were to Arm themſelves.</p>
            <p>While the Friends of the Duke of <hi>Braganza</hi> were thus buſy at <hi>Lisbon</hi> in advancing his Affairs,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:40321:44"/> he himſelf was employ'd in ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Provinces; the Firſt Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter alarm'd by theſe Delays, diſpatch'd away a Courier, with expreſs Orders for him to come immediately to Court, and to prevent his making any pretence of Want of Money, he ſent with him an Order for Ten Thouſand Ducats on the Royal Treaſury.</p>
            <p>This was plain and intelligible Language. The Duke could not defer his Journey without juſtly rendring himſelf ſuſpected: He could not with any Colour of Reaſon diſpenſe with obeying the King's Meſſage; and had Grounds to conclude, That all farther De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays would ſoon bring ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome Orders from <hi>Madrid,</hi> which would break all his Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:40321:45"/> and ruin his Enterprize. And therefore, to make an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of complying with the King's preſſing Commands, he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd the greateſt part of his Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold to ſet forward for <hi>Madrid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He gave all neceſſary Orders during his Abſence: He diſpatch'd away a Gentleman at the ſame time to the Vice-Queen, to give her notice of his Departure. He writ to the Firſt Miniſter to aſſure him, that he would be at Court within Eight days at fartheſt; and to have all things repreſented to the beſt advantage, he brib'd the Courier with a Sum, under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a Gratuity for his Care and Diſpatch in bringing the King's Orders to him. At the ſame time he acquainted the Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:40321:45"/> with theſe freſh Orders, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before them the Neceſſity of putting their Deſigns in execution on the Day which was agreed on, for fear of being prevented by the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there was an Obſtacle which hinder'd them from at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting any thing ſo ſuddenly. There was a Man of Quality at <hi>Lisbon,</hi> who ſhew'd on all Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions a violent Hatred of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Government. He would ever be Railing againſt them, calling them Tyrants and Uſurpers, and declaiming againſt their Injuſtice and Oppreſſion; above all, he would ever be venting his Spleen on the Expedition into <hi>Catalonia,</hi> and making a Thouſand diſmal Prognoſticks on it. <hi>D' Almada</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:40321:46"/> having frequently convers'd with him, did not believe any Man could more heartily wiſh the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of <hi>Portugal,</hi> or would be more tranſported to hear of any Deſigns on foot for the effectual Reſtoring of its Liberty. But, Gods! how he was aſtoniſh'd, when taking him aſide, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint him with this Conſpiracy! He found him as fearful and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in Action, as he had appear'd daring in Words. He began now to excuſe himſelf from having any ſhare in this matter, or being concern'd in this Plot, pretending there was no good Grounds to proceed on; and the ſame Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who ſo Bold and Brave when the Thing was remote, was now become timorous, and ſcar'd at
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:40321:46"/> the Proſpect of the leaſt Danger; <hi>Where,</hi> ſays he to <hi>d' Almada, are thoſe Forces which are neceſſary to ſupport a Deſign of this nature? What Army have you to oppoſe the</hi> Spaniſh <hi>Troops, which will be poured into the Country upon the firſt Motion of this kind? What Great Men have you to appear at the Head of you?</hi> Or, <hi>have they a Fund ſufficient to bear the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of a Civil War? I'm afraid, that inſtead of Reſtoring the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of</hi> Portugal, <hi>your Attempt will only prove deſtructive to it, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the</hi> Spaniards <hi>with a Pretence, which they have long ſought for, to accompliſh the Ruin of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>D' Almada,</hi> who expected no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs than Expreſſions of this kind, enrag'd to find he had
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:40321:47"/> truſted his Secret in ſo ill hands, gave no other Anſwer; but draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Sword, his Eyes ſparkling with Rage, reply'd, <hi>Falſe Man! either thou ſhalt take my Life, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with my Secret, or I will make thee an Example for having thus ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd my Credulity by thy Lyes and Impoſture.</hi> The other, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways held it Prudent to avoid the Danger which was neareſt, at the ſight of a drawn Sword con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to all that <hi>d' Almada</hi> had propos'd, and offer'd to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Conſpiracy, finding Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to invalidate thoſe he firſt gave; he ſwore with repeated Oaths again to keep the Secret in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violably: In ſhort, he forgot no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that might perſuade <hi>d' Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> that it was neither Courage, nor
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:40321:47"/> want of Reſentment againſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> which had kept him from agreeing to the Propoſal as ſoon as he had made it.</p>
            <p>However, <hi>d'Almada</hi> did not dare to rely on his Oaths and Aſſuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but was mightily diſturb'd at this Accident; And keeping a watchful Eye on this Man, he gave notice to the Conſpirators of this Adventure. The Alarm was ſoon ſpread, and ſeveral Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexions were made on the Levity and Inconſtancy of this Man; and they began to fear, That the View of Danger, or the Hopes of a Great Recompence, ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce him to prove Treacherous in ſpite of all their Care for Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention. On this Conſideration they reſolv'd to defer the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:40321:48"/> of their Plot, and oblig'd <hi>Pinto</hi> to write to his Maſter to forbear till he receiv'd farther News from them. But <hi>Pinto,</hi> who very well knew of what Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance it is to defer the Day in Matters of this Nature, writ pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately to that Prince to have no Regard to his Letter, as proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only from a Panick Fear in the Conſpirators, which would certainly vaniſh before the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger could arrive at <hi>Villa-vicioſa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo it happen'd; for the next Morning finding every one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue unſhaken, they began to be aſham'd of taking ſo hot an Alarm; and he who was the chief Cauſe of this Uneaſineſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a little better ſettled (either by a greater Generoſity of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:40321:48"/> or Apprehenſion of the bad Conſequence of accuſing ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Great Men) they reſolv'd to adhere to the Day firſt agreed on. But ſcarce was this Difficulty over, but another aroſe, which did not create leſs Diſquiet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pinto</hi> had taken Care to place divers of the Conſpirators about the Palace to obſerve all that paſs'd. Theſe, as they appear'd to walk idly up and down, the Night before the Execution, which was to begin with the Death of <hi>Vaſconcellos,</hi> ſaw that Miniſter Embark on the <hi>Tago.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>None beſides the Conſpirators could have drawn any Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from this, ſince a Thouſand ſeveral Occaſions, in which they
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:40321:49"/> had not the leaſt ſhare, might carry him over the River. But their Jealouſy was ſo great, that an Alarm was inſtantly ſpread amongſt them. They immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately concluded this Crafty, Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Miniſter, who had his Spies in every Corner, had diſcover'd ſomething of their Plot. They made no Doubt his going over the Water was with deſign to ſend ſome of the Troops which Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd in the Neighbouring Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, into the Town. The Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the moſt terrible Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the Horrors of Death preſented it ſelf to their Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; they fancied their Houſes ſurrounded with Officers of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; and ſome began to think of flying into <hi>Africk</hi> or <hi>England</hi>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:40321:49"/> to eſcape the Cruelty of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards.</hi> They paſs'd away part of the Night under theſe terrible Apprehenſions, as it were between Life and Death, when ſome of the Conſpirators, who kept about the Court, came to inform them, That the Secretary was return'd with <hi>Hautboys</hi> Sounding before him, he only having been at an Entertainment on the other ſide of the Water. This News put an End to all their anxious Thoughts, and made them all joyful; and ſo each Man depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, being well aſſur'd there was nothing ſtirring in the Palace, and that all there ſlept in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Security, not once dream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the next Day's Action.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:40321:50"/>
            <p>It was very late when they parted; and from that time, to the Minute of the Execution, there were but a few Hours of Night, notwithſtanding a conſiderable Accident happen'd in that Space; which ſhews us how full of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty and Hazard all Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes are, where the Fear of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, or the Hope of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, may tempt Men to be Treacherous and Faithleſs. <hi>George Mello,</hi> Brother to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Horſe, moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lodg'd at the Houſe of one of his Relations, in one of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burbs, at a ſmall Diſtance from the City. This Gentleman thought that the Minute of the Plot break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out being now at hand, his Relation, who had for a long
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:40321:50"/> time been his intimate Friend, might juſtly reproach him if he ſhould conceal a matter of that Importance from him, in which the other was equally concern'd with himſelf for the Common Good of his Country: That he could eaſily engage him in the Conſpiracy, and bring him with him to the Rendezvouz. Upon this Conſideration, as ſoon as he was return'd to his Lodging, he goes up to his Kinſman's Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and taking him into his Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, communicates the Enterprize to him, urging him to join with ſo many Worthy Perſons, and to behave himſelf like a Man of Honour, and a true <hi>Portugueſe.</hi> The Other was ſurpriz'd with ſo ſtrange a Piece of News; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:40321:51"/> he ſtrove to ſhew a ſort of Joy to find his Country was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Point of Recovering its Liberty. He thank'd <hi>Mello</hi> for the Confidence he had honour'd him with, and aſſur'd him, he ſhould eſteem it a Happineſs to expoſe his Life, and be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to have a ſhare of Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger with ſo many brave Men in ſo Juſt and Glorious a Cauſe.</p>
            <p>After this they parted to take a Repoſe of ſome few Hours; <hi>Mello</hi> was ſcarcely in his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber before he began to Repent of his Exceſſive Confidence, and to blame himſelf for having put the Fate of ſo many Worthy Men into the Hands of a Perſon he was not entirely aſſur'd of. He
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:40321:51"/> thought he diſcover'd in his Eyes and Countenance a ſecret Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſineſs, and the Marks of Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize and Apprehenſion at the Proſpect of ſo Dangerous an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize. In ſhort, he was afraid the Fear of Puniſhment, and the Hopes of a Certain Reward, might prevail with him to make a Diſcovery.</p>
            <p>Full of theſe Tormenting Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections he walk'd about his Chamber; when hearing a ſort of muttering Noiſe, and ſeveral Perſons talking low, he opened his Window to hear what they ſaid: And by the Help of a Dim-light he diſcover'd his Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man at the Door, ready to mount on Horſeback. At this being fired with Rage, he ſoon
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:40321:52"/> came down; and running with his drawn Sword at him, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, <hi>What made him out of Doors at that time of Night? What his Buſineſs was, and whither he was going?</hi> The other being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly ſurpriz'd, endeavour'd to give ſeveral indifferent Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; but <hi>Mello</hi> threatning to kill him, conſtrain'd him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn again into his Chamber, and took the Keys along with him, and kept him under his Eye till the Time of Action, and then brought him with him to meet the other Conſpirators.</p>
            <p>At length the Day was come when the Event was to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine whether the Duke of <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganza</hi> deſerv'd the Title of King,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:40321:52"/> and Deliverer of his Country, or that of Rebel and Enemy of the State.</p>
            <p>The Conſpirators came early to the Houſe of <hi>Dom Miguel d' Almeida,</hi> and the other Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, where they were to Arm themſelves. They all appear'd there with ſo much Reſolution and Confidence, they ſeem'd to go to a certain Victory. It was remarkable, that in ſo great a Number of Clergymen, Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, and Gentlemen, all acted by different Intereſts, not one Man out of the whole Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber fail'd in his Word and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: Every one was as impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient for the Moment of Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, as if he had been Chief,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:40321:53"/> and Author of the Enterprize, and expected the Crown for the Recompence of the Dangers which he expos'd himſelf to. Divers Ladies coveted a ſhare in this Glorious Exploit; and Hiſtory has preſerv'd the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of <hi>Dona Philippa de Ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> who Arm'd both her Sons with her own Hands; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhe had put on their Cui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſſes, <hi>Go, my Children,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>put an End to Tyranny, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge your ſelves of your Enemies; and be aſſured, that if your At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt fail of Succeſs, your Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will not ſurvive one Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Misfortune of ſo many brave Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:40321:53"/>
            <p>All being thus Armed, made their way to the Palace, and divers of them went in Chairs to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal their Number and Arms. They divided themſelves into four Bodies, as was agreed, waiting with a great deal of Impatience till the Clock ſtruck Eight, which was the preciſe Moment of Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution. Never did Time ſeem ſo long; the fear of having their Number obſerved, or that the early Hour they appeared before the Palace, might give the Secretary any Suſpicion, made them very uneaſie. At length it ſtruck Eight a Clock, and <hi>Pinto</hi> having fired a Piſtol, they all took the Signal.</p>
            <p>Each Man charged briskly in the Poſt aſſigned him, <hi>Dom Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guel d' Almeida,</hi> with his Party,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:40321:54"/> fell on the <hi>German</hi> Guard, who being unprovided, and deſtitute of Arms, were ſoon defeated, and that almoſt without making any Reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>The Maſter of the Horſe, <hi>Mello</hi> his Brother, and <hi>Dom Eſtevan d' Acugna</hi> attacked the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, which lay before that part of the Palace which is called the Fort. In this he was ſuſtained by thoſe Townſmen who were concerned with him. Theſe Men, with their Swords in their Hands, forced the <hi>Corps de Garde</hi> where the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were retrenched. But none made a more conſiderable Figure than a Prieſt of the Town, who marched at the Head of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators, with a Crucifix in one Hand, and a Sword in the other,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:40321:54"/> exhorting the People to cut their Enemies in Pieces, and charging the <hi>Spaniards</hi> himſelf with the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Fury. All fled before him; for appearing Arm'd, with an Object that Religion teaches us to revere, no Perſon dar'd to hurt him. Thus, after a ſlight Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Officer and his Soldiers were forced to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and ſave their Lives, by crying as the reſt did, <hi>God ſave</hi> the Duke of <hi>Braganza, King of</hi> Portugal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pinto</hi> having thus made his way to the Palace, put himſelf at the Head of thoſe who attacked the Apartment of <hi>Vaſconcellos.</hi> He marched with ſo much Aſſurance and Reſolution, that happening to meet one of his Friends, who
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:40321:55"/> asked him, trembling, where he was going with that number of Armed Men, and what he was about to do. <hi>Nothing,</hi> replied he ſmiling, <hi>but to dethrone a Tyrant, and reſtore a lawful Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In entring the Secretaries A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment they met <hi>Franciſco Soa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez d' Albergeria,</hi> the Civil Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant<note n="*" place="bottom">Corrigidor de Civil.</note> who was juſt going out of his Lodgings. This Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate thinking the Tumult only proceeded from a quarrel, offer'd to interpoſe his Authority, to end the Fray. But hearing them cry on all ſides, <hi>God ſave the</hi> Duke of <hi>Braganza,</hi> he thought the Honour and Duty of his Place obliged him to cry, <hi>God ſave the King of</hi>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:40321:55"/> Spain <hi>and</hi> Portugal, which coſt him his Life, one of the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators ſhooting him inſtantly dead, proud to have this occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to puniſh his ill-timed Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antonio Correa,</hi> firſt Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner of the Secretary, ran out upon the firſt Noiſe. This Man was the common Inſtrument of his Cruelties; and after the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of his Maſter, treated the Nobility with great Contempt, <hi>Dom Antonio de Menezes,</hi> plunged his Dagger in his Breaſt. This Blow could not make the Wretch ſenſible his Power was at an End, but imagining in this Aſſault they had miſtaken him for another, he turned in a Rage to <hi>Menezes,</hi> crying, <hi>Dogs, How dare you ſtrike
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:40321:56"/> at me:</hi> The other without reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, redoubled his Thruſts, and laid him on the Ground, weltring in his Blood. However, theſe Wounds did not prove Mortal, and he eſcaped at that time, to loſe his Life after with more Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominy, by the Hands of the common Executioner.</p>
            <p>The Conſpirators having thus treated the Commiſſary, who had ſtopt them for a ſmall while on the Stairs, forced into the Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries Chamber. He had then with him <hi>Diego Garcez Palleia,</hi> a Captain of Foot, who ſeeing ſuch a multitude of People enter Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and enraged miſtruſted a deſign on the Life of <hi>Vaſconcellos.</hi> Tho' he had no obligation to that Miniſter, the generoſity of
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:40321:56"/> his Temper made him throw himſelf out of the Door, with his Sword in his Hand, to diſpute the Entry of the Conſpirators, and give the Secretary time to make his Eſcape, but receiving a Hurt in his Arm, and being diſabled from holding his Sword, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt by the Multitude, he threw himſelf out of a Window, and had the good Luck to eſcape with Life.</p>
            <p>Immediately the Conſpirators ruſhed in a Crowd into the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretaries Lodgings, they ſearched for him every where, overturned the Beds, opened the Coffers, and every one was eager to have the Honour of the firſt Blow.</p>
            <p>However, all this while he was no where to be found, and the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:40321:57"/> Conſpirators were reduced to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, and enraged to think he ſhould thus eſcape their Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, till an Old Woman Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant being threatned with Death, pointed to a Wall in which ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Arms were hid, and here they found him buried in Papers.</p>
            <p>The Conſternation he was in at the apprehenſion of immediate Death, which he ſaw before him, would not ſuffer him to ſpeak the leaſt Word. <hi>Dom Rodrigo de Saa</hi> gave him the firſt ſhot with a Piſtol, after which the reſt of the Conſpirators ſtabbed him, and threw his Body out of the Window, crying, <hi>The Tyrant is diſpatched, God preſerve our Liberty, and</hi> Dom John, <hi>King of</hi> Portugal.</p>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:40321:57"/>
            <p>The Crowd about the Palace, ſeeing them throw out the Body, received it with great Shouts and Acclamations. Every one offer'd ſome Indignity to the lifeleſs Trunk, as if by this means they hoped to revenge the Oppreſſion of their Country, and give a Blow to Tyranny.</p>
            <p>This was the Fate of <hi>Michael Vaſconcellos,</hi> a <hi>Portugueze</hi> by Birth, but an Enemy to his Country, and a <hi>Spaniard</hi> by his Inclination. He had by Nature an admirable <hi>Genius</hi> for Buſineſs, was a Man of great Ability and Application, of a marvellous Induſtry, fruitful in Inventing new Methods of drawing Money from the People, and, by conſequence, void of all Pity, Inflexible and Rigorous,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:40321:58"/> even to Cruelty: He had no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to Kindred, Friends, or other Conſiderations: No Man had any Aſcendant over him, he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible to all Pleaſures, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of being touched with any Remorſe of Conſcience: He had heaped together immenſe Wealth, by his Place, part of which was plunder'd in the Heat of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, the People pretending to do themſelves Right for the Damages they ſuſtained during his Miniſtery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pinto,</hi> without loſing Time, marched to join the other Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, who were order'd to make themſelves Maſters of the Palace, and ſeize the Perſon of the Vice-Queen: He found this was done already, and that all Parts
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:40321:58"/> of their Deſign had been crown'd with equal Succeſs. In ſhort, thoſe who were appointed to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack the Apartment of the Princeſs, preſenting themſelves before the Gates, and the furious Multitude threatning to ſet fire to them, if they did not forthwith open them, the Vice-Queen, attended with her Maids of Honour, and the Archbiſhop of <hi>Braga,</hi> preſented her ſelf at her Chamber-Door, flattering her ſelf that her Preſence would appeaſe the Nobility, and oblige the People to withdraw. <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> ſaid ſhe, advancing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the principal of the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators, <hi>the Secretary has juſtly drawn on himſelf the Odium of the People, and your Indignation, by his haughty and inſolent Carriage; and now his
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:40321:59"/> Death has deliver'd you from ſo hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a Miniſter, methinks your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment ought to be ſatisfied? Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, Gentlemen, theſe Diſorders may as hitherto be imputed to your Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred againſt the Secretary; but if you perſiſt any longer in this Tumultuous manner, you will be guilty of Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, and render me unable to make any Defence for you to the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dom Antonio de Menezes,</hi> replied, <hi>That it was a Folly to think, that ſo many People of Rank had appeared in Arms to take away the Life of a Wretch, who ought to have loſt it by the Hands of the common Hangman; That they were met together to reſtore the Duke of</hi> Braganza <hi>to a Crown, that rightfully belonged to him, and had been uſurped by Strangers, and they would ſacrifice their Lives with
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:40321:59"/> Pleaſure, to replace him on the Throne.</hi> She was about to reply, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe the King's Authority, but <hi>d' Almeida</hi> fearing that any longer Parley might abate the Heat of the Conſpirators, interrupted her, telling her in ſhort, <hi>Portugal owned no other King than the Duke of</hi> Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganza, and the Conſpirators im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately gave a ſhout, each ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to outvie the other, <hi>God ſave</hi> Don John, <hi>King of</hi> Portugal.</p>
            <p>The Vice-Queen ſeeing the Torrent had broke all bounds, thought ſhe ſhould find more O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience in the City, and that her Preſence would have more Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on the People and Townſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, when the Conſpirators were not there to encourage them. But as ſhe offered to go down, <hi>Don
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:40321:60"/> Carlos Norogna</hi> intreated her to keep in her Chamber, aſſuring her ſhe ſhould be ſerved with the ſame Reſpect, as if ſhe had ſtill the Command of the Kingdom, telling her, He did not judge it by any means convenient, to expoſe the Perſon of ſo great a Princeſs to the Inſults of the Multitude, who were all in Tumult, and full of Zeal for their Liberty. She ſoon underſtood ſhe was his Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, and vext, demanded in a diſdainful manner, <hi>And what can the Mobb do to me?</hi> To which <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogna</hi> replied, in a very great Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Nothing, Madam, but throw your Highneſs out of the Windows.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Archbiſhop of <hi>Braga</hi> was incenſed at theſe words of <hi>Norogna,</hi> and ſnatching a Sword from a
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:40321:60"/> Soldier near him, attempted in an outragious manner to throw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf thro' the Conſpirators, to kill him, and revenge the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front done to the Vice-Queen; but <hi>Dom Miguel d' Almeida</hi> embracing him, conjured him to conſider the danger to which he expoſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and taking him aſide by force, told him, his Life had not coſt nothing: That he had had a great deal of difficulty in obtaining it, from the Conſpirators, to whom his Perſon was odious enough, that he had no farther need to exaſperate them by a Piece of Bravery ſo ill-timed, and ſo little agreeable to a Perſon of his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter. By this means he was perſwaded to withdraw, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble his Paſſion, hoping Time
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:40321:61"/> would give him a more favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able occaſion of ſhewing his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment, and his Devotion to the Intereſt of <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reſt of the Conſpirators ſecured the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who were in the Palace or the City: They ſeized on the Marqueſs <hi>de la Pueiba, Major domo</hi> to the Vice-Queen, and eldeſt Brother to the Marqueſs <hi>de Leganez, Dom Didaco Cardevas,</hi> —Major-General, <hi>Dom Fernant de Caſtro,</hi> Intendant of the Marine; the Marqueſs <hi>de Bainetto,</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Uſher to the Vice-Queen, and ſeveral Sea-Officers who were in the Port. All this was done with as little Diſturbance as if they had been apprehended by Orders from the King of <hi>Spain.</hi> No Man ſtirred to aſſiſt them,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:40321:61"/> and themſelves were not in a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to reſiſt, being for the moſt part taken in their Beds.</p>
            <p>In the next place, <hi>Antonio de Saldania,</hi> at the Head of his Friends, with a vaſt Crowd following him, went up to the ſovereign Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Juſtice; He made a ſhort Speech to the Company, diſplay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Happineſs of</hi> Portugal, <hi>that now had regained her Natural Lord:</hi> telling them, That Tyranny was now at an End: That the Laws would be re-eſtabliſhed, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice have its ancient Courſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Government of ſo Wiſe and Juſt a Prince. This Speech was received with a general Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, and anſwered by loud Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations; and all Decrees made in the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s Name were
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:40321:62"/> changed, and ſtiled, By the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and in the Name of <hi>Dom Juan,</hi> King of <hi>Portugal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whilſt this Gentleman obliged the Chamber of Juſtice to own the Duke of <hi>Braganza</hi> for their King, <hi>Dom Gaſton Contingno</hi> ſet free thoſe whom the Severity of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Miniſters had confined. Theſe poor Men paſſing in one Moment from a gloomy Dungeon, and the continual fear of Death, to the delightful view of the Liberty of their Country, tranſported with Gratitude, and dreading the return of their Chains, made up a new Company, who did not ſhew leſs Ardour to eſtabliſh the Throne of the Duke of <hi>Braganza,</hi> than the Body of the Nobility, who formed the firſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign.</p>
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:40321:62"/>
            <p>In the midſt of this general Gladneſs, which the Succeſs of the Enterprize gave the Conſpirators, <hi>Pinto,</hi> and ſeveral of the Chief were extreamly uneaſie. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> were ſtill in the Citadel, from whence they could batter the Town, and ſoon give them occaſion to repent of their haſty Joy: Beſides, this was a Port where the King of <hi>Spain</hi> could re-enter the City at pleaſure; therefore thinking they had done nothing till they were Maſters of the Place, they went to the Vice-Queen, and demanded an Order from her for the Governour to put that into their Hands.</p>
            <p>She rejected the Propoſition with Scorn, reproaching them with their Rebellion, and asking
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:40321:63"/> them diſdainfully, if they inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to make her an Accomplice. <hi>D' Almeida,</hi> mad at her Refuſal, all on Fire, and his Eyes ſpark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with Rage, ſwore that if ſhe did not ſign this Order, without farther delay, he would inſtantly ſtab all the <hi>Spaniards</hi> they had in Cuſtody. The Princeſs, ſurpris'd at the Paſſion of the Man, and fearing ſo many People of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity might loſe their Lives, thought the Governour knew his Duty too well to pay Obedience to an Order which he muſt needs ſee was extorted by Force, and upon this Conſideration ſhe Signed it, but this had a very different Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect from what ſhe imagined. The Spaniſh Governour, <hi>Dom Louis del Campo,</hi> a Man of ſmall
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:40321:63"/> Reſolution, ſeeing ſo many of the Conſpirators in Arms, and follow'd by a vaſt Crowd of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who threatned to tear him and the whole Garriſon in pieces, if he did not inſtantly Surrender, was glad to come off ſo cheaply, and have ſo good a pretence to cover his Cowardice, ſurrendred the Citadel, and tamely delivered it into their Hands. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators having thus ſecured all ſides, diſpatched away <hi>Mendoza</hi> and the Maſter of the Horſe to the Duke of <hi>Braganza,</hi> to carry him the News, and to aſſure him from the City, that there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wanting to compleat their Joy, but the Preſence of their King.</p>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:40321:64"/>
            <p>However, this was not equally deſired by all Perſons. The Great Men of the Kingdom could not ſee his Elevation without a ſecret Envy, and moſt of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, (who had no ſhare in the Conſpiracy) were ſilent, waiting for the Iſſue before they would declare their Sentiments. Nay, ſome proceeded ſo far as to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, whether that Prince would own an Action which would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly have ſuch terrible Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences. Above all the reſt, the Creatures of <hi>Spain</hi> were in a ſtrange Conſternation, not a Man of them daring to ſtir, for fear of irritating the People, furious with their new Liberty, and every one kept himſelf cloſe at Home, till Time ſhould ſhew what they
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:40321:64"/> had to Fear or Hope from the Deſigns of the Duke of <hi>Braganza.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But his Friends, who were well informed of his Intentions, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued their way. They met at the Palace to give Orders, till their New Maſter ſhould arrive, and unanimouſly declared the Archbiſhop of <hi>Lisbon,</hi> Preſident of the Council, and Lieutenant-General for the King. He ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed himſelf at firſt, repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them, that the preſent State of the Kingdom required a General, rather than a Man of his Character, in ſuch a Poſt. But at length pretending to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with the Importunity of his Friends, he conſented to take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the ſigning the Orders, provided the Archbiſhop of <hi>Braga</hi>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:40321:65"/> were appointed for his Colleague in the management of Buſineſs, and all Diſpatches till the King's Arrival.</p>
            <p>By this Device, that crafty and politick Prelate hoped, under Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of ſharing an Authority with him, to render the other an Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice and Criminal in the Eyes of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> if he accepted the Offer; or in caſe he refuſed, to ruin him with the King, and render him Odious to the People, and all <hi>Portugal,</hi> as a declared E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy of that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The Archbiſhop of <hi>Braga</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Snare laid for him, but being wholly devoted to the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,</hi> and in the Intereſts of the Vice-Queen, he refuſed perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to have any ſhare in the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:40321:65"/> Government. So the Archbiſhop of <hi>Lisbon</hi> had it alone, and <hi>Dom Miguel d' Almeida, Pedro Mendoza,</hi> and <hi>Dom Antonio d' Almada</hi> were appointed as Counſellors of State to aſſiſt him.</p>
            <p>One of the firſt Cares of this Governour, was to ſeize the three great <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Galleons in the Port of <hi>Lisbon.</hi> For this purpoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Barks were fitted out, into which the Youth of the City threw themſelves: They diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd an eager deſire to gain Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in this Exploit, but little Oppoſition was made, the Officers and greateſt part of the Soldiers being ſeized in the City, at the Time when the Conſpiracy broke out.</p>
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:40321:66"/>
            <p>The ſame Evening he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched Couriers to exhort the People to give Thanks to God for the Recovery of their Liberty, with Orders to the Magiſtrates of each City to proclaim the Duke of <hi>Braganza,</hi> King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and ſecure all the <hi>Spaniards</hi> they could find. In ſhort, he made all Preparations at <hi>Lisbon,</hi> for the magnificent reception of their new Maſter. The Archbiſhop gave notice to the Vice-Queen, that it would be convenient ſhe ſhould leave the Palace, and make room for the King and his Houſhold, and ordered an Apartment to be prepared for her in the Royal Houſe of <hi>Xabregas,</hi> at one end of the Town. The Princeſs left the Palace as ſoon as ſhe received
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:40321:66"/> this Meſſage, but with a haughty Air, not ſpeaking one word, and paſt thro' the City thither. And now, far from a Crowd of Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers attending her, ſhe had ſcarce any of her Domeſtick Servants with her, only the Archbiſhop of <hi>Braga,</hi> ſteady to her Intereſts, gave her publick Marks of it on this Occaſion, at a time when he could not do it without an appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent hazard of his Life.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the Duke of <hi>Braganza</hi> endured great Convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Mind, reflecting on his uncertain Deſtiny, and at once his Breaſt was fill'd with all the various Images with which Hope can flatter, or Fear torment a doubtful Mind. The diſtance of
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:40321:67"/> 
               <hi>Villa Vicioſa,</hi> which is thirty Leagues from <hi>Lisbon,</hi> prevented his being informed of what paſſed ſo ſoon as he earneſtly wiſhed. All he knew was, that his Life and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune lay at Stake, and that Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Minute muſt decide his Fate. He had reſolved at firſt, as was noted above, to raiſe all the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties under his Dependencies, but after he judged it better to expect News from <hi>Lisbon,</hi> and act his Part conformably to what ſhould paſs there.</p>
            <p>There only remained the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Algarba,</hi> and the City and Citadel of <hi>Elvas,</hi> which he could retire to, if Succeſs fail'd in the Capital City; and if the Plot ſhould miſcarry, he thought he ſhould eaſily excuſe himſelf from
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:40321:67"/> having a ſhare in it, at a Time when the <hi>Spaniards</hi> would be glad to have him Innocent.</p>
            <p>He had planted ſeveral Couri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers on the Road to <hi>Lisbon;</hi> and tho' he expected News every Hour, he had paſt the whole Day, and a great part of the Night in diſturbance, till at length <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doza</hi> and <hi>Mello,</hi> with extream di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, arrived at <hi>Villa Vicioſa.</hi> They threw themſelves inſtantly at the Prince's Feet, and by this reſpectuous Action, and the Joy which ſhone in their Face, they diſcover'd to him, ſooner than they could by any Expreſſions, that he was King of <hi>Portugal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They would have given him an exact Account of the Succeſs of their Enterprize; but the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:40321:68"/> Prince, without giving them Time to enter into the particulars of this Affair, conducted them, with ſome Impatience, into the Dutcheſſes Apartment. Theſe two Lords complimented her in the ſame manner as if ſhe had already been upon the Throne, and aſſured her of the Hearty Wiſhes of her Subjects, and as a Mark they own'd her for their Sovereign, they treated her with the Title of Her Majeſty, which was the more agreeable, ſince the Kings of <hi>Portugal,</hi> before that Time, had only taken that of Highneſs.</p>
            <p>It is eaſie to judge how migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was the Joy of the Prince and Princeſs, if we reflect on the great uneaſineſs they were freed from,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:40321:68"/> and the high Station they were raiſed to. The Caſtle reſounded with Acclamations, and the News ſpread it ſelf every where in a Moment. And the ſame Day he was proclaimed King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> in all the Cities of his Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dances. <hi>Alphonſo de Mello</hi> did as much in the City of <hi>Elvas,</hi> whole Crowds came in to pay their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to their new King; and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably theſe firſt Homages, tho' paid in a confuſed and diſorderly manner, did not leſs pleaſe that Prince, than thoſe after on a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Day of Ceremony.</p>
            <p>The King ſet forward for <hi>Liſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon,</hi> with the ſame Equipage, which ſeem'd deſign'd for the Court of <hi>Spain.</hi> He was accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied by the Marqueſs <hi>de Ferrara,</hi>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:40321:69"/> his Kinſman, the Count <hi>de Vimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſa,</hi> and a great number of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Quality which met him there.</p>
            <p>He left the Queen, his Wife at <hi>Villa Vicioſa,</hi> to keep the Province firm to his Obedience. He found the Ways lined on both ſides, with an infinite number of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which flocked to ſee him, and had the pleaſure to hear the Shouts of the People, wiſhing his Proſperity, and loading the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> with all the Curſes they could invent. The whole Body of the Nobility, the Great Officers of the Crown, and the firſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, went out in ſeveral Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to receive him, at a great diſtance from <hi>Lisbon,</hi> and he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd the City, amidſt the Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:40321:69"/> and Applauſe of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, follow'd by a numerous and magnificent Court, fill'd with Joy.</p>
            <p>At Night were ſeveral Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works in divers publick Places of the Town. Each Citizen had one before his Door, and the Windows ſhone with an infinity of Candles and Flambeaux, that the whole City ſeemed one Flame, which made a <hi>Spaniard</hi> ſay, <hi>That Prince was very Fortunate, to gain ſo fair a Kingdom for a Bonefire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Inſurrection at <hi>Lisbon</hi> was inſtantly followed by the General Revolt of the whole Kingdom, and the Revolution was ſo ſpeedy and general, that each City ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have a Plot ripe for Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, after the Example of their Capital. Couriers arrived hourly
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:40321:70"/> with Advice, that Cities, and entire Provinces had expelled the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and ſubmitted to the King. The Governours of the other Places had not more Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution than him of <hi>Lisbon,</hi> and either for want of Troops, or other Warlike Proviſions, or for want of Courage they went off ſhamefully, and for the moſt part without once Firing. Every one feared the Fate of <hi>Vaſconcellos,</hi> and nothing appeared ſo terrible as an enraged Multitude. In ſhort, they fled like ſo many Criminals eſcaped out of Priſon, and not one <hi>Spaniard</hi> was to be ſeen in the whole Kingdom, except thoſe who were detained; and all this in leſs than a Fortnight's Time.</p>
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:40321:70"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Dom Fernand de la Cueva,</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of the Citadel of Sir <hi>Juan,</hi> at the Mouth of the <hi>Tago,</hi> was the only Perſon who made ſome reſiſtance, and pretended to keep the Place for the King his Maſter. This Garriſon, compoſed only of <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and commanded by brave Officers, made a vigorous Oppoſition, upon the firſt Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of the <hi>Portugueſes.</hi> To reduce this Place, they thought it neceſſary to Beſiege it in Form; and for this purpoſe brought their Canon down from <hi>Lisbon;</hi> the Trenches were opened, and they made their Advances as far as the Counterſcarp, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the continual Fire, and frequent Sallies of the Beſieged; but a Treaty being the ſafeſt
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:40321:71"/> and ſhorteſt way to gain the Place, the King (in fine) made the Governour ſuch advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous Offers, that he had not Power to ſtand out any longer. He was dazled with the great Summs offered, and having a Commend of the Order of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which the King promiſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr on him. In ſhort, the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles were agreed on, and the Place Surrendred, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the endeavours of the Officers to the contrary, who refuſed to Sign the Capitulation: Of this number was <hi>Dom Rodrigo de Cha lon,</hi> a young Gentleman of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daluſia,</hi> of great Valour, who commanded a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Terce in that Place, and offered to hold out three Weeks longer, till they
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:40321:71"/> ſhould receive Aid from <hi>Spain,</hi> which they had Intelligence were put to Sea, under the Command of the Duke of <hi>Maqueda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King thought it beſt not to deferr his Coronation any longer, to confirm his Authority, and render his Perſon more Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt to the People. The Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony was obſerved on the 15th of <hi>December,</hi> with all poſſible Magnificence. The Duke <hi>d'Aveiro,</hi> the Marqueſs <hi>d' Villareal,</hi> the Duke <hi>de Camino</hi> his Son, the Count <hi>de Monſano,</hi> and the reſt of the Great Men of the Kingdom aſſiſted at the Solemnity. The Archbiſhop of <hi>Lisbon,</hi> at the Head of his Clergy, accompanied by ſeveral Biſhops, received him at the Gate of the Cathedral, and he
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:40321:72"/> was ſolemnly acknowledged as King of <hi>Portugal</hi> by all the States of the Kingdom, who took the Oath of Fidelity to him.</p>
            <p>A few Days after the Queen arrived with a numerous Train. The whole Court went a great way out of Town to meet her; The Officers who were appointed to compoſe her Houſhold were gone before, and the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf went out of <hi>Lisbon</hi> to receive her. This Prince omitted no Magnificence which might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his new Dignity, or might give the World a Mark, how much he thought ſhe contributed to place the Crown on his Head. It was remarkable, that in ſo great a Change ſhe was not in the leaſt embaraſs'd, but ſupported
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:40321:72"/> her new Character with ſo much Grace and Majeſty, that ſhe ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed born in a Throne.</p>
            <p>Thus was that great Enterprize happily finiſhed, which may be accounted a Miracle, conſidering the vaſt number, and different Characters of Perſons entruſted with the Secret. No Cement could ever have made ſo firm an Union, but that Hatred to the Spaniſh Government, an Antipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy as ancient as the Monarchy it ſelf, ariſing from the perpetual Wars, frequent between Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring States, and after foment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Concurrence of both Nations in diſcovering the <hi>Indies,</hi> and their Difference in matters of Trade.</p>
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:40321:73"/>
            <p>The News of the Revolt was ſoon brought to the Court of <hi>Spain.</hi> The Miniſter was enraged to find all his Meaſures broken, and ſo fair a Kingdom loſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all hopes of retrieving. The King, his Maſter, had no occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for new Buſineſs: He found Difficulties enough to defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf againſt the united Arms of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Holland;</hi> but above all, the Revolt in <hi>Catalonia</hi> was of dangerous Conſequence, and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated in his Mind a thouſand anxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Cares.</p>
            <p>All the Court knew how Things went, and the King was the only Man who remained ignorant, and no one dared inform him, dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Diſpleaſure of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, who would never have par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:40321:73"/> an Offence of this Nature. At laſt, this Affair making too much noiſe to be concealed any longer, the <hi>Conde</hi> Duke fearing ſome of his Enemies ſhould at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to relate the Matter to his Diſadvantage, reſolved to diſcloſe it to the King. But knowing the Temper of that Prince, he thought to give this ſuch a Turn, that he ſhould not know the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of his Loſs; and for this end, coming to him with a ſeeming Openneſs and Aſſurance. <hi>Sir,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I bring your Majeſty a piece of good News, Your Majeſty is juſt now become Maſter of a fair Dutchy, and a large Eſtate.</hi> How ſo? replied the King, all ſurprized, <hi>I ſhall explain my ſelf,</hi> ſays the Miniſter, <hi>the Duke of</hi> Braganza
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:40321:74"/> 
               <hi>has been lately Giddy, and ſuffered himſelf to be ſeduced by the Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and proclaimed King of</hi> Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal. <hi>By this Act all his Eſtate is Confiſcated, and Your Majeſty may reunite it to Your Revenue; and by the Extinction of that Family, enjoy that Kingdom, without fearing any Diſturbance for the future.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding this Prince was a very weak Man, he was not ſo dazled with theſe magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent Hopes, but he ſaw this was no eaſie matter. But not daring to ſee with other Eyes than thoſe of his Miniſter, he only replied coldly, <hi>That he hoped he would uſe all Diligence to ſuppreſs this Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, which if let alone might have dangerous Conſequences.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:40321:74"/>
            <p>The King of <hi>Portugal</hi> neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing which might eſtabliſh his new Greatneſs. Immediately after his arrival at <hi>Lisbon,</hi> he na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for Governours of the Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier Places, Men of the moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Valour, Fidelity, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience; all which had Orders to depart ſtrait, with all the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers they could get together; and to uſe all poſſible Diligence to put their ſeveral Forts in a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of Defence. He delivered out Commiſſions for raiſing Men, and immediately after his Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation, called a Convention of the States of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>In this Aſſembly, to prevent all Doubts, he cauſed his Title to be examined, and, by a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Act, was acknowledged to
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:40321:75"/> be the True and Rightful King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> as deſcended by the Princeſs his Mother, from the Infant <hi>Edward,</hi> Son to King <hi>Ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel,</hi> to the Excluſion of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> who was deſcended from the ſame King by a Daughter, who farther was, by the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Laws of the Kingdom, diſabled, by being married to a Foreign Prince.</p>
            <p>He declared to this General Aſſembly of the States, that he would content himſelf with his Patrimonial Eſtate, for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of his Houſhold, and would reſerve the Royal Revenue for the Neceſſities of the Kingdom, and to make the People reliſh the ſweetneſs of his Government, he aboliſhed all Impoſts, which the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:40321:75"/> 
               <hi>Spaniards</hi> had laid on them.</p>
            <p>He filled all the moſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Poſts and Employs in the State with thoſe Conſpirators which had ſhewn the greateſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour in this Revolution. <hi>Pinto</hi> had no ſhare in this Promotion, the Prince not thinking his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority well enough ſettled to place one of his Domeſticks of a mean Extraction, in any principal Place. Notwithſtanding this, his Power with the King and People was not leſs; and without the Title of a Miniſter, or Secretary of State, he performed the Office, by the great Confidence the King had in him.</p>
            <p>Having thus given all the good Orders imaginable, within the Kingdom, he bent his Thoughts
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:40321:76"/> next to Foreign Princes. He di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatched able Embaſſadors to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure himſelf to be owned, to make Alliances, and raiſe new Enemies to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> He made a League Offenſive and Defenſive with the <hi>Hollanders</hi> and <hi>Catalonians,</hi> and obtained aſſurance of the Protection of <hi>France.</hi> The King of <hi>Spain</hi> diſcovered his Weakneſs, by attempting no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing conſiderable on the Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers of <hi>Portugal</hi> all the Campaign, probably becauſe the Revolt in <hi>Catalonia</hi> employed all his Strength. All his Attempts were unſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and his Troops ſtill came off with diſadvantage. Some time after News came that <hi>Goa,</hi> and other Places, under the Dominion of the <hi>Portugueſe</hi> in the <hi>Indies,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:40321:76"/> Africk,</hi> and <hi>Peru,</hi> had followed the general Revolution of the Kingdom; every thing ſeemed to promiſe the King of <hi>Portugal</hi> a <hi>Series</hi> of Succeſs, and a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom quiet at Home, and Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious abroad. But obſerve the uncertainty of Human Greatneſs, how this Prince, in the midſt of his Proſperities, and the careſſes of Fortune, was upon the Point of periſhing, and loſing at once his Life and Crown by a horrid Conſpiracy, ſilently formed in <hi>Lisbon,</hi> within the Walls of his own Court.</p>
            <p>The Archbiſhop of <hi>Braga</hi> was, as I related before, wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> and one of their Miniſters in <hi>Portugal.</hi> He plainly ſaw he could never
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:40321:77"/> hope to be reſtored till the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Government ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhed; beſides, he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid the King, who ſeemed at firſt to have ſome reſpect to his Character, in forbearing to ſeize him with the reſt of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Miniſters, might nevertheleſs do it when his Authority was better ſettled. But the moſt potent Motive that put him upon any conſiderable Action, was his Zeal for the Vice-Queen. He could not endure to ſee that Princeſs in Priſon in a place where he thought She had a Right to Reign; but above all, he was exaſperated to be refuſed ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance to her, which was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied him, and divers other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Quality, when it was found She only made uſe of this
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:40321:77"/> Liberty to inſpire Rebellion into thoſe who reſorted to her. This Proceeding ſeemed to him Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical, and an intolerable Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and he could not but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent to himſelf, that Princeſs every Moment demanding her Liberty from him, as a juſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn for thoſe Favours he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from her. Theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections kindled a Rage in the Breaſt of this Prelate; and made him reſolve to employ all means to expreſs his Gratitude, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge her on her Enemies. And conſidering it would be difficult to ſurprize or corrupt the Guards ſet over her, he reſolved to go directly to the Spring, and by killing the King, to reſtore at once, that Princeſs her Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:40321:78"/> and her former Authority.</p>
            <p>Having concluded on this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, he applied himſelf to find means to put his Project in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution as ſoon as poſſible, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he ſhould not long continue in his Place of Preſident of the Palace, and be oblig'd to retire to <hi>Braga.</hi> He concluded ſtrait, he muſt take a different Step from that which, the King had taken. He never hoped to gain the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by reaſon of their natural Hatred to the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> on the other ſide, the reſtoring of the King being the Work of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, it was certain they would never engage in a Conſpiracy of this kind, he plainly found he could only apply himſelf to the Great Men, who were not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:40321:78"/> in this Revolution, and uneaſie at the Duke of <hi>Braganza</hi>'s Fortunes. And therefore having firſt ſecured Protection of the Miniſter of <hi>Spain,</hi> he caſt his Eyes on the Marqueſs of <hi>Villareal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He repreſented to that Prince, That <hi>the New King being of a timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and diffident Temper, would lay hold of all Opportunities to ruin, or at leaſt diminiſh the Greatneſs of his Family, to ſecure the Crown to his own Poſterity.</hi> That <hi>He, and the Duke</hi> d' Aveiro, <hi>both of the Blood Royal of</hi> Portugal, <hi>had no Employs conferr'd on them, whilſt all Places of Profit and Truſt in the Kingdom, were given as a Recompence to a parcel of Seditious Fellows.</hi> That <hi>all Men of Honour were concerned to ſee him thus contemptuouſly uſed.</hi> That <hi>he
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:40321:79"/> muſt conſume his Life in a mean in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>activity, and be buried in the Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of his Country-Seat.</hi> That <hi>He ought to conſider his High Birth and Fortunes rendred him too Great to be a Subject to ſo petty a King.</hi> That <hi>He had loſt in the King of</hi> Spain, <hi>a Maſter who had ſeveral Kingdoms and Governments in his diſpoſal; and was able to give him an Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſuitable to the Greatneſs of his Condition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing this Diſcourſe made an Impreſſion on the Mind of that Prince: He added, <hi>That he had Order from the Court of</hi> Spain <hi>to promiſe him the Vice-Royalty of</hi> Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal, <hi>as the Reward of his Fidelity:</hi> However, this was not in any manner the Intention of that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, who aimed at nothing more
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:40321:79"/> than the Liberty and Reſtoration of the Dutcheſs of <hi>Mantua:</hi> But more powerful Motives were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to engage the Marqueſs <hi>de Villareal.</hi> The Conſiderations which the Archbiſhop laid before him, prevailed with him to be the Head of the Conſpiracy, with the Duke of <hi>Camino</hi> his Son.</p>
            <p>The Archbiſhop being well aſſured of theſe two Princes, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged the Grand Inquiſitor, his intimate Friend. This Man was of great Conſequence to the Archbiſhop's Deſign, becauſe with him he brought in all the Officers of the Inquiſition, a Race of Men which have ever been more formidable to Honeſt Men, than Raſcals, and bear a great ſway amongſt the <hi>Portugueſe.</hi> He la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:40321:80"/> to convince him it was his Duty, reminding him of his Oath of Fidelity to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> which he pretended he ought not to break in favour of a Rebel: Farther he urged, it could not be his Intereſt to adhere to the New King, ſince neither of them could hope long to enjoy their Places, under a Prince who conferr'd all Employs on his own Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>He ſpent ſome more Months in gaining over more Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors: The principal of which were the Commiſſary <hi>La Cruſada,</hi> the Count <hi>d' Armamar,</hi> Nephew to the Archbiſhop; the Count <hi>de Ballerais, Dom Auguſtin Emanuel, Antonio Correa,</hi> the ſame Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary of <hi>Vaſconcellos,</hi> whom <hi>Menezes</hi>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:40321:80"/> had given divers Stabs on the breaking out of the Plot; <hi>Lorenzo Pidez Carrable,</hi> Keeper of the Royal Treaſury, all Creatures of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> to whom they owed their Places and Fortunes, which they could not hope to retain long, without the return of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Government.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews,</hi> who are very nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous at <hi>Lisbon,</hi> and live there, by making an outward ſhew of the Chriſtian Religion, had a ſhare in this Conſpiracy. The King had lately refuſed very conſiderable Sums, which they had offer'd him to put a ſtop to the Proceedings of the Inquiſition, and to obtain a Permiſſion for the publick Profeſſion of their Religion. The Archbiſhop craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:40321:81"/> made uſe of their Reſentment to engage them in this Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize. He had private Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences with ſeveral of the Chiefs of the Party, who dreaded to think they had thus unſeaſonably declared themſelves; and by this means expoſed themſelves to the Severities of the Inquiſition.</p>
            <p>This Crafty Prelate improv'd the Confuſion they were in to his Advantage, and immediately aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd them of his Protection with the Grand Inquiſitor, whom they all knew to be at his Devotion. In the next place, he endeavour'd to raiſe a Jealouſie, inſinuating, That a Prince who affected Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotry, would certainly drive them out of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and promiſed them Liberty of Conſcience, and
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:40321:81"/> a Synagogue in the Kingdom, if they would contribute to the Reſtoration of the late Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>So violent was the Paſſion of the Archbiſhop, he did not bluſh to uſe the aſſiſtance of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of JESUS CHRIST, to dethrone his rightful Prince; and perhaps this was the firſt time the inquiſition ever acted in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cert with the Synagogue.</p>
            <p>The Conſpirators, after vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Projects, at laſt reſolved on this, which was the ſenſe of the Archbiſhop, and had been agreed between him and the Prime Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of <hi>Spain:</hi> That in the dead of the Night, of the Fifth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhould ſet Fire to the four Corners of the Palace;
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:40321:82"/> and at the ſame time to ſeveral Houſes in different Parts of the City, to keep the People em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in quenching thoſe next their own Dwellings. That the Conſpirators ſhould throw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the Palace, under Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of aſſiſting to extinguiſh the Fire; and in the midſt of that Hurry and Confuſion which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends Accidents of this kind, they ſhould thruſt in near the King's Perſon, and ſo ſtab him. That the Duke of <hi>Camino</hi> ſhould, in the mean time, ſecure the Queen, and the young Princes, juſt as the Princeſs of <hi>Mantua</hi> had before been, as Hoſtages for the Surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Citadel. That Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations ſhould be made to fire thoſe Veſſels which were in Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:40321:82"/> That the Archbiſhop, and the Grand Inquiſitor, with all his Officers, ſhould march thro' the City to appeaſe the People, and prevent any Commotion by the dread of the Inquiſition: And that the Marqueſs <hi>de Villareal</hi> ſhould take upon him the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, till farther Orders ſhould arrive from <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But having no Aſſurance the People would declare for them, they needed Troops to ſupport this Action. To this end it was agreed to ſollicit the <hi>Conde</hi> Duke to ſend a conſiderable Fleet on the Coaſts, to be ready to enter the Harbour at the Moment the Conſpiracy ſhould be put in Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. That upon the firſt notice of the Succeſs, he ſhould give
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:40321:83"/> Orders to all the Troops on the Frontiers to march directly to <hi>Lisbon,</hi> to make Head againſt all Oppoſition.</p>
            <p>But the Conſpirators found great difficulty in ſettling this ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Correſpondence with the Prime Miniſter. Aſſoon as the King was informed the Vice-Queen had writ to <hi>Madrid,</hi> he had placed ſo ſtrict a Guard on the Frontiers, that no Perſon could go out of the Kingdom without his expreſs Leave; and it was not judged ſafe to corrupt the Guards, for fear they ſhould prove Treacherous, and deliver the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters up, or diſcloſe the Practices uſed to corrupt them.</p>
            <pb n="157" facs="tcp:40321:83"/>
            <p>At length being preſt with the neceſſity of acquainting the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Miniſter with their Intentions, without which, all the Meaſures they ſhould take would be vain; and doubtful what way to effect this, they caſt their Eyes on a Rich Merchant of <hi>Lisbon,</hi> who was Treaſurer of the <hi>Douane,</hi> who, upon the Account of his great Dealings in ſeveral Parts of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> had a Permiſſion to write into <hi>Caſtile.</hi> This Man, named <hi>Baeze,</hi> made a Publick Profeſſion of the Chriſtian Religion, but was one of thoſe whom the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugueſe</hi> call New Chriſtians, who are ſuſpected to obſerve in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Rites. They of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd him a very great Sum of Money to engage in this Affair.
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:40321:84"/> This joyn'd with the Importunity of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who were in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret of this Conſpiracy, deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined him, he accepted their Offers, and undertook to have their Letters deliver'd to the <hi>Conde</hi> Duke <hi>d' Olivarez.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He addreſſed his Packet to the Marqueſs <hi>d' Aiamonte,</hi> Governor of the firſt Frontier Place in <hi>Spain,</hi> not doubting they were ſafe as ſoon as out of the Dominion of <hi>Portugal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Marqueſs, who had a private Intereſt in the Affairs of <hi>Portugal,</hi> being nearly Allied to the Queen, ſurprized to find Letters with the great Seal of the Inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on affixed to them, and addreſſed to the Firſt Miniſter of <hi>Spain,</hi> inſtantly open'd them, fearing they might
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:40321:84"/> contain ſome Particulars of his Private Correſpondence with the King and Queen of <hi>Portugal,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the late Revolution, but found in them, to his no ſmall Amazement, the Project and Plan of a Conſpiracy, which was ripe for Execution, and aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to deſtroy him and the whole Royal Family.</p>
            <p>He ſent the Packet back to the King of <hi>Portugal.</hi> His ſurprize was unſpeakable, to find, upon opening the Letters, that Princes nearly Allied to him, an Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop, and ſeveral of the Chief Men in his Court, who ſhewed the greateſt Joy at his Elevation, ſhould ſo ſoon Conſpire to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive him at once of his Life and Crown.</p>
            <pb n="160" facs="tcp:40321:85"/>
            <p>He ſummoned a Council pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately, and ſome Days after act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to the Reſolutions then taken. The Fifth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> was the Day when the Plot was to be put in execution, about Eleven a Clock at Night, the Particulars of which were ſet down in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercepted Papers. The ſame Day the King ordered all the Troops quarter'd in the Neighbouring Villages, to march into <hi>Lisbon,</hi> under a Pretence of a General Review in the great Court of the Palace. He gave privately, with his own Hand, ſeveral Billets ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to thoſe about him, in whom he moſt confided, with ſtrict Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders not to open them till Noon, and then to execute punctually, the Orders contained in them.
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:40321:85"/> In the next place, taking the Archbiſhop, and the Marquis <hi>de Villareal</hi> into his Cloſet, under pretence of Communicating ſome Buſineſs to them, he ſecured them without noiſe, about Noon, and a Captain of the Guards ſeized on the Duke of <hi>Camino,</hi> in the Great Square. Thoſe who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Billets, opening them, found Orders to ſeize ſome of the Conſpirators, and commit them to ſuch and ſuch Priſons, and to ſet a Guard on them till farther Orders. Theſe Meaſures were ſo well taken, and ſo punctually executed, that in leſs than an Hours time, the whole Forty ſeven were ſeized, no one having No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice to make his eſcape.</p>
            <pb n="162" facs="tcp:40321:86"/>
            <p>The noiſe of this Plot being ſpread thro' the Town, the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple flocked to the Palace in great Crowds, demanding the Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to be delivered to them. Tho' the King was pleaſed to ſee the Affection of his New Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; yet this unuſual Concourſe made him a little uneaſie. He feared theſe popular Tumults might grow frequent, which he look'd on as no better than Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Aſſemblies. So having thanked the People for their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for his Perſon, and aſſured them Juſtice ſhould be done, he ordered the Magiſtrates to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſe them.</p>
            <p>However, leſt the Heat of the People ſhould abate, who eaſily paſs from the moſt violent Fury
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:40321:86"/> and Rage, to Sentiments of Pity and Compaſſion, this Prince gave out, the Conſpirators had a Deſign to Aſſaſſinate him, and the whole Royal Family, to ſet the City on Fire, and ſeize what eſcaped the Flames as their Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: And to prevent all Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies for the future, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge their Vengeance, they had reſolved to People the Town with a Colony of <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and to ſend the Citizens to the Mines in <hi>America,</hi> and bury them alive in that Abyſs, which had ſwallowed a World of People.</p>
            <p>In the next place, he appointed Judges out of the Supreme Court of Judicature, for the Tryal of the Conſpirators; to theſe he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, two of the Grandees of the
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:40321:87"/> Kingdom, upon the Account of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Braga,</hi> the Marqueſs of <hi>Villareal,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Camino.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King ordered the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners not to make uſe of the Letters which he put into their Hands, if they could Convict the Plotters without them, for fear the Court of <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould come to know by what means they came to fall into his Hands. But there was no need to employ them to diſcover the Truth. <hi>Baeze</hi> contradicted himſelf in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the Queſtions which were put to him; and this Wretch, on the firſt Torture, confeſs'd his Guilt, and diſcloſed the whole Plan of the Conſpiracy. He owned they had a Deſign to kill
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:40321:87"/> the King; that the Office of the Inquiſition was full of Arms, and they only waited the <hi>Conde</hi> Duke's Anſwer for the Execution of their Deſigns.</p>
            <p>Moſt part of the other Plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters being put to the Queſtion, their Depoſitions were agreeable to thoſe of the <hi>Jew.</hi> The Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop, the Grand Inquiſitor, the Marquis <hi>de Villareal,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Camino</hi> confeſſed their Guilt, to avoid the Torture. The Judges condemned the two laſt to be Beheaded, and the reſt to be Hang'd and Quarter'd, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the Sentence of the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men for the King.</p>
            <p>The King ſummoned a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil immediately, and told his Miniſters, he feared the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:40321:88"/> of ſo many Perſons of Rank, tho' they were Guilty, might have bad Conſequences. That the chief Conſpirators being of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the firſt Houſes of the Kingdom, their Kindred would be ſo many ſecret Enemies of the Government, and the deſire to revenge their Death, would be the unhappy ſource of perpetual Plots. That the Death of Count <hi>Egmont</hi> in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and of the <hi>Guiſes</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> had both fatal Conſequences; that to Pardon ſome, and inflict a leſs ſevere Puniſhment than Death, would win the Hearts of all Perſons, and oblige them, their Relations and Friends, to act by motives of Gratitude. That however his private Opinion was for Mildneſs,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:40321:88"/> he had aſſembled them to have their ſenſe, and reſolved to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed as they judged beſt.</p>
            <p>The Marquis <hi>de Ferrara</hi> was for having them Executed without delay. He aſſerted with vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence, that a Prince on theſe Occaſions, ought to hear nothing but Juſtice; that Mildneſs was dangerous, and to pardon Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals of this kind, would be thought a Weakneſs in a Prince, proceeding more from a Fear of their powerful Friends, than a natural Goodneſs: That Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity would bring the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment into Contempt, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage their Friends to deliver them out of Priſon, and poſſibly to puſh Matters further. That an Example of Severity was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:40321:89"/> upon his Acceſſion to the Crown, to deterr others from the like Attempt. That this Offence was not only againſt the King's Perſon, but againſt the State, and a deſign to ſubvert the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. That he ought to conſider more the Juſtice he owed his People, than his Inclination to Clemency, at a Time when the Preſervation of his Perſon, and the Publick Safety, were inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
            <p>All the Council being of the ſame Opinion, the King yielded, and the Sentence was executed the next Day. The Archbiſhop of <hi>Lisbon</hi> interceeded for the Life of one of his Friends, and ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited the Queen, with all the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of a Man, who thought
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:40321:89"/> nothing could be refuſed to his Services. But the Queen, who underſtood very well the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of impartial Juſtice, how much a diſtinction of this Nature would exaſperate the Friends of the reſt, only replied, with a Tone which ſhewed her inflexible Reſolution. <hi>My Lord, the greateſt Favour I can grant you, is to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get that you ever ſpoke to me of this Matter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King fearing to draw the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> on him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing to make uſe of the good Graces of the Holy Father, that he might own him as King, changed the Puniſhment of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Braga,</hi> and the Grand Inquiſitor, into a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Priſon. The Archbiſhop
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:40321:90"/> died of Grief, becauſe his deſign had miſcarried. The Vice-Queen was delivered to the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> and the firſt Miniſter of <hi>Spain</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing clandeſtine ways unable to deſtroy the King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> was reſolved to attack him by open force. But this too was ſtill un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucceſsful. This Prince kept a conſiderable number of Troops on his Frontier, commanded by the beſt Generals, and compoſed of a great number of Foreign Officers and Voluntiers, whom his Bounty had drawn into his Service. Beſides this, he had the dexterity to make Penſioners in the very Council of <hi>Spain,</hi> who ſerved him effectually, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſed Matters ſo, that thoſe Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals who were ordered to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:40321:90"/> 
               <hi>Portugal,</hi> were never in a Condition to attempt any thing conſiderable to its prejudice. Thus he reigned ſeventeen Years, the Delight of his Subjects, and the Terror of <hi>Spain.</hi> After his Death, the Queen, a Princeſs of Courage and great Skill in the Affairs of Government, gloriouſly kept the Crown and Fortune for her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. She ſhone with full Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor on the Throne, during the whole time of her Regency, and ſhewed all thoſe Qualities in their brighteſt Luſtre, which made her one of the moſt Illuſtrious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes that ever reigned. The Conduct and the Art of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were her chiefeſt Care, and her conſtant Study. She applied her ſelf with great aſſiduity, to
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:40321:91"/> unmask the ſeveral Characters, and gueſs by the moſt nice and fine outſides, the moſt conceal'd Intentions; and if at any time ſhe happen'd to be deceiv'd, ſhe would trace the ſeveral Steps to find the Original Miſtake. By her extraordinary Diligence ſhe had attain'd to great Skill and Judgment; the <hi>Spaniſh</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Ad haec politicas artes, bonos &amp; malos Regiminis dolos, dominationis arcana, humani latibula ingenii non modo intelligere Mulier, ſed &amp; pertractare quoque &amp; provehere tam Naturâ quam Diſciplinâ mirifice inſtructa fuit. <hi>Caetan Paſſar. de Bello Luſitan.</hi>
               </note> Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans as well as the <hi>Portugueze,</hi> do her the Juſtice to own, ſhe could ſee the naked Hearts of her Courtiers, tho' veiled with the moſt artful Diſſimulation. In
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:40321:91"/> ſhort, where there appear'd any thing Great or Glorious to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, ſhe wanted neither Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to conquer all Difficulties, or Wit to find means to obtain what ſhe deſired; and there was nothing farther to be wiſhed for in this matchleſs Woman, except a more true Notion of real Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or higher Motives than Fame and Glory.</p>
            <p>The Court of <hi>Spain</hi> thinking the Regency the moſt favourable opportunity to regain their loſt Power in <hi>Portugal,</hi> bent the force of their Arms on that Kingdom. The Penſioners of the late King, in the Councils of <hi>Madrid,</hi> who had hitherto diverted the Storm, were dead, and the Regent had no way left but to prepare
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:40321:92"/> for War. She obtain'd of the Princes, her Allies, the beſt Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, and the moſt experienced Officers. The weight of Affairs did not make any Impreſſion on her. Her Capacity, Wit, and ſteady Courage were proof a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Adventures. Nothing but the Throne ſhe fill'd could have ever ſhewn the great Genius of this Princeſs, wiſe in her Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, impenetrable in her Deſigns, rigid and inflexible in maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every Point of her juſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. The People had a great Affection to her Government. Fear and Reſpect kept the Great Men of the Kingdom in a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Submiſſion. Never Troops were in better Condition, or bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Diſciplin'd: Her Orders were
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:40321:92"/> executed as punctually as if ſhe had been at the Head of her Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in Perſon. Every one knew Offences to the prejudice of the Queen's Affairs were never par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd. All Men were diligent in doing their Duty: She would know every thing, read all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatches, and nothing eſcaped her Care and Providence.</p>
            <p>To conclude, She put every thing in ſo good Order, in the time of her Regency, that King <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> her Son, upon his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into the Government, found the Kingdom in a Condition to maintain a War againſt <hi>Spain,</hi> with Advantage, his Generals won great Battels, and ever beat their Enemies; ſo that ſome time after the Abdication of that Prince,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:40321:93"/> 
               <hi>Spain,</hi> wearied with ſo fruitleſs and expenſive War, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to deſire a Peace of <hi>Dom Pedro,</hi> his Brother, now reigning, and own him Rightful King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and that Crown, inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 4. line pen. dele <hi>then.</hi> p. 6. for <hi>Moguel,</hi> r. <hi>Miguel.</hi> p. 11. after the Crown, inſert, <hi>were not Criminal.</hi> p. 16. for <hi>Ozono.</hi> 1. <hi>Ozorio.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>MEmoirs of the moſt Material Tranſactions in <hi>England,</hi> for the laſt Hundred Years, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding the Revolution in 1688. By <hi>James Wellwood,</hi> M. D. Phyſician in Ordinary to His Majeſty, and Fellow of the College of Phyſicians, <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Tim. Goodwin,</hi> at the <hi>Queen's-Head</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt St. <hi>Dunſtan</hi>'s-Church in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:40321:93"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
